<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Saints like Christ: or, somewhat of truth delivered to the congregation at headly in Hampshire By Jo. Symmonds, M.A.</title>
            <author>Symonds, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6357</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222482</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833649</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833649</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38127</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62109)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38127)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2219:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Saints like Christ: or, somewhat of truth delivered to the congregation at headly in Hampshire By Jo. Symmonds, M.A.</title>
                  <author>Symonds, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 147, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the Black Spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. D C. L. [1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Dr. Williams' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Saints --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38127:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SAINTS LIKE CHRIST: OR, Somewhat of truth deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Congregation at <hi>Headly</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Jo. Symmonds,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 COR. 15.48.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>As is the heavenly, ſuch are they alſo that are heavenly.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Black Spread-Eagle</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls. M.DC.L.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:38127:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38127:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Nobly Deſcended, gratious Chriſtian and vertuous Virgin, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
               </hi> S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SANNA MILDMAY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe you,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have made bold in venturing into the world to make uſe of your Worſhips name, that ſo I may paſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ith the leſſe moleſtation in theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oubleſome times. It is an age of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ouble, and that not alone in the
<pb facs="tcp:38127:3"/> world, and amongſt men of the world, but ſuch that profeſſe to Chriſt, and I hope are in Chriſt. Theſe latter own themſelves, and what is theirs as men and fleſhly, too much; and what is Chriſts and ſpirituall not enough; The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in the church of <hi>Corinth</hi> partly aroſe from mens overmuch affecting ſingularity, one was of <hi>Paul,</hi> another of <hi>Appollo,</hi> another of <hi>Cephas,</hi> another of Chriſt. It may be ſome boaſted of their circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, ſome of their Baptiſme, ſome of both Baptiſme and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, ſome it may be gloried that they had medled neither with Baptiſme nor circumciſion; if not ſo, yet it is more then conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall that ſome boaſted that they were hearers of ſuch a one, and of ſuch a ones Congregation: and from this outſide-worke highly extolling their choice and way, ſlighting and abaſing others,
<pb facs="tcp:38127:3"/> caus'd ſtrife. The Apoſtle blames for this contention, and ſhews that the way of Chriſt is to take from men, as men, all glorying. It is unbeſeeming the eye to hate the foot, becauſe the foot ſees not, 'tis enough that it is of the body: ſo ſhould not Chriſtians that have more excellent gifts, villifie them that have not attained to their perfection, or trouble to ſee others differing in judgement in ſome low things from them; for in the body of Chriſt unity may ſtand with diverſity: there may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity in reſpect of forms and yet unity in ſpirit; for men may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy God in different formes, God may dwell in them that regard a day, and in them that regard it not; God may communicate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to them, and ſo make them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like within glorious; by enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his glorious preſence. Formes are to be reverenc'd (knowing of
<pb facs="tcp:38127:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſome there is uſe) as they wherein Chriſtians may walke and be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full one to another; yet meer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in forms makes not Saints, nor doth uniformity in formes breed true unity. True unity of members is from thoſe members union with the head. And as ſouls are in unity with the head; ſo will they grow into a unity one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. 'Tis the new and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all birth whereby ſouls are one with Chriſt, and like Chriſt that makes them at on with Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and true Chriſtians look upon all that profeſſe to Chriſt not as in formes, but as poſſeſſing Chriſt; and as they find Chriſt living in them do they eſteeme them, and account them precious, knowing that a precious Chriſt makes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Chriſtians, and that they will keep their excellency let the times and places be never ſo bad they are caſt into. Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="tcp:38127:4"/> you are young, and yet ſome bad dayes you have ſeen, people of all Ages, Sexes, qualities very bad, ſome ill ſavour in every place by reaſon of corruption have you to your annoyance met withall; And God knowes what more you may, whileſt here in the body. You know what hath kept you right in theſe croſſe-walkings, and alſo what hath preſerv'd you and enabled you to keep your ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, hath not a Chriſt guided you? hath not a Chriſt communicated himſelfe to you? I have high thoughts of your Noble ſelf, and I am perſwaded never a whit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove you, but that you are as high as I take you to be, and that is in Chriſt; whom you have found all in all unto you, and on whom you rely to carry you through what remaines of ſufferings as your part and portion, that at laſt you may ſit down with Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:38127:5"/> in his Throne even as he is ſet down with his Father, in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Throne: and as you are ſuch as he is in this world, ſo you may be like him in the world to come, participating with your ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and bleſſed redeemer in his glory to your perfect happines. You have an inſide like Chriſt now, a ſoul glorious; you ſhall have an outſide like him alſo, body glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, body and ſoul glorious, all glorious. Towards the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which ſo farre as my day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prayers may help, you ſhall be ſure of them, praying to God on your behalfe. And upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I tender my ſelfe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips devoted Servant, to ſerve you, in what I may, <hi>JO. SYMMONDS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38127:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 John 4.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>As he is, ſo are we in this world.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which makes Chriſts appearance delightfull &amp; giving ſoul-content to Chriſtians is love, &amp; that which makes the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Chriſtians de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful and pleaſant to Chriſt is love.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Simele gaudet ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mili.</hi> Joh. 13.1 1 Joh. 4.19</note> Like is very much won and pleas'd with its like, a loving Chriſt with lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſtians, and loving Chriſtians with a loving Chriſt: A merciful Chriſt with merciful Chriſtians, and merciful Chriſtians with a merciful Chriſt: A holy Chriſt with holy Chriſtians, and holy Chriſtians with a holy Chriſt.<note place="margin">Cant. 1.2</note> Chriſts love to Saints is better then wine,<note place="margin">Cant. 4.10</note> ſo is the Saints love to Chriſt much better then wine, The ſavour of the good ointments of Chriſt cauſeth the Virgins to love him,<note place="margin">Cant. 1.3</note> and the ſmell of the ointments and garments of thoſe Virgins, being holy Saints, and Chriſts
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38127:6"/> Spouſe,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.5, 6, 7</note> is like the ſmell of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> where pleaſant and odoriferous trees, herbs and ſpices grew in abundance; No ſpices (not the beſt nor ſweeteſt of all Created things) yielded ſo pleaſant a ſavour to Chriſt as the graces,<note place="margin">Cant. 4.10</note> and actings of thoſe graces, of his Siſter and Spouſe did.</p>
            <p>Chriſtians, you ſee your bleſſed ſtate, you are like Chriſt,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.20 Rom. 1.5</note> and lov'd of him, it may be you are neither like men of the world, nor lov'd of them, you may be never the worſe for this,<note place="margin">Jo. 15.19</note> nay, it may be the more happier, for differing ſo much from them, and being hated or ſlighted of them. Our conformity to the world Chriſt never commends, but on the contrary (in Scripture) often diſcommends and bids us beware of it;<note place="margin">Eph. 5.11 Rom. 12.2 Mat. 20.25, 26 2 Cor. 6.14</note> 'Tis conformity to himſelf that Chriſt invites unto and expects, and as Chriſt would have it ſo, Saints deſire it may be ſo; They care not who diſapproves of them and theirs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Cor. 4.3</hi> Humanum diem vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium.</note> ſo Chriſt approves, who blames them, ſo Chriſt commends them, who ſlights them, ſo Chriſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours them; They (it may be) cannot ſay when they ſee rich-men, that they are like them, rich as they are rich;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38127:6"/> or if they ſee men advanced to worldly honours, that they enjoy ſuch honours and dignities, or if they ſee people beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull or gorgeouſly apparel'd, they cannot (it may be) ſay they have ſo faire a face or rich cloaths, &amp;c. Saints think they are rich enough, honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough, that they are very faire and gallant, if like Jeſus Chriſt. In reſpect of many worldly injoyments that the ſons of men poſſeſſed, 'tis probable the ſons of <hi>Zion</hi> could not ſay they were like them, yet this was their comfort, that they had the witneſſe of the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16</note> that they could ſay they were like God, they were holy ſouls, like the holy God; union with God brought forth likenes to God;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 John 4.15, 16</hi> Deus cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas eſt, quid preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſius? Et qui manet in charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, in Deo manet, quid ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius? Et Deus in eo, quid jucundius? Haec gloria chriſtianorum magna eſt.</note> a bleſſed God dwelling in them makes them bleſſed ſouls; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding bleſſed and ever happy are they, that from in-dwellings of Father Son and Spirit in them, can ſay God is holy, Chriſt is holy, the Spirit holy, and we as Saints delight to be holy, and ſo to be like Father, Son and Spirit: The Apoſtle ſpeaks largely in his own and Saints commendation in uttering a few words, ſaying, <hi>As he is, ſo are we in this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38127:7"/> world:</hi> He had ſpoken much of God, and of the Son of God,<note place="margin">1 Joh 4.16</note> and of Gods dwelling in Saints, and of Saints being born of God,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.7</note> and knowing God, and having laboured with his Divine and Heavenly Rhetorick, he endeavoured to give God the honour due unto him, and he would not let ſlip an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of magnifying the grace of God in Saints,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.1 1 Joh. 5.12</note> and how much they were dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by enjoying God, and as to extol their greatneſſe and goodneſſe in the world, ſo to chear up themſelves, that had received ſuch kindneſs of God, and that they might with boldneſſe ſtand up pleading their own dignity and bleſſedneſs,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.14</note> againſt all the reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, diſgraces and ſcorns of the world, he holds out God, and then himſelf and Saints: <hi>As he is, ſo are we in this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhall look upon the Text as it hath relation mainly to God, as making out himſelf to us in Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Loquitur hic de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitate, in puritate &amp; inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae. Hem. <hi>1 Pet. 1.15 2 Cor. 5.21. Luk. 6.36.</hi>
               </note> and to Saints through grace enjoying God within, and by that enjoyment ſtriving to be like God in holineſſe, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, mercy, love, patience, longſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, goodneſſe, gentleneſſe, &amp;c. And although 'tis impoſſible for Chriſtians
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38127:7"/> to be ſuch as God for purity and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,<note place="margin">Haec con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitas noſtri cum Deo in imitatione &amp; cona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u, &amp; omni puritate &amp; perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſita eſt. <hi>Rom. 8.29</hi>
               </note> yet through the Spirits help may they imitate God, and for the manner of living holily, ſtrive to be conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Lord, So that as God is a God of love, Chriſtians are Chriſtians of love: that love that is in a Chriſtian to God, it is but a ſon, it is but a fruit of the love that is in God to a Chriſtian, 'tis but the ſpringing forth of ſomewhat of God himſelf planted within in the ſoul,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.7</note> 'tis but a ſtream run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning back to that Sea from whence it came, returning God his due; like for like; love for love; a Saint knows love deſerves love; Gods love is love;<note place="margin">1 Jo. 4.19</note> In this way of love he acts freely,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.2</note> and ſo is like God, it is as ordinary for a Chriſtian to love, as to live; for what maintains his being as a Saint, produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth love to the ornament of his being. As it rejoyceth in having the life of a Saint,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.20 Act. 4.20 Pſal. 40.8</note> ſo it is pleaſed in doing the work of a Saint, laying out it ſelf in what is pleaſing to the Lord;<note place="margin">Joh. 7.18</note> God cannot but act what is good, and what tends to his own glory; take a Saint as having God living in it,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.18, 19.</note> and from that living of God in it acting, it doth what is good,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38127:8"/> and alſo tends to the glory of God;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.58</note> It knows 'tis not loſt labour to be doing for God, and that it is not in vaine. There is infinite good in God, and there is ſome good in a Saint; Infinitneſſe in God enables God for infinite worke, God is able to do like himſelf, beyond what a ſoul can think or conceive; A ſoul that enjoyes ſomewhat that this all-good-God gives out in his love through Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10</note> is in his actings accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what he receives, and as that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ſprings and ſprouts out;<note place="margin">Omnia gratiae di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinae tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit.</note> A ſpark of fire will do what a ſpark can do, and a drop of water what a drop may: indeed it cannot do ſo much as the Sea, or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement of fire can do; 'Tis a Chriſtians joy that of Chriſts heavenly fulneſſe it receives ſome grace,<note place="margin">Joh. 3.34</note> Chriſt hath what he hath without meaſure, a Chriſtian in meaſure; a Chriſtian is glad that it finds Chriſt ſaying,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.48</note> 
               <hi>As is the heavenly ſuch are they that are heavenly,</hi> and that by the ſpirits work 'tis faſhioned to be like Chriſt now 'tis in the world, and ſo chang'd into the ſame Image from glory to glory.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.18</note> And though it live in a wicked world amongſt wicked men, yet it is not like them, but it is like him
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38127:8"/> that is heavenly, it is not conformable to thoſe it lives withall without in the body, but to him that lives within, in his ſoul; Dearly beloved, what are you? what can you now ſay for your ſelves? can you ſay you are like Chriſt? have you a life like Chriſt? have you a converſation like Chriſt? are you cloath'd like Chriſt?<note place="margin">Col. 3.12</note> have you put on (as the Elect of God (holy and belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) bowels of mercies, kindneſſe, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of mind, meekneſſe, long ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, forbearing one another, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving one another, if any man have a quarrel againſt any,<note place="margin">Chriſtus non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum nobis eſt donum, verum eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum. Miraculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae actiones Chriſti, mentem noſtram de veritate doctrinae ipſius con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmabunt. Peculiares actiones, quae ſunt ipſius officii propriae, hae ut expiatoriae peccati noſtri fuerunt: ita ſalutis fiduciam in nobis alent &amp; confirmabunt.</note> even as Chriſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave you, ſo alſo do yee: The actions of Chriſt ſhould be inſtructions of chriſtians, yet conſider rightly of Chriſts actions, ſome were miraculous, as faſting forty daies, raiſing the dead, &amp;c. theſe are not to be immitated, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot, yet theſe may help to ſtrengthen our faith, and confirme us concerning the truth of the Doctrine of Chriſt. Some are peculiar actions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to his office, as to redeem, or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38127:9"/> make interceſſion, &amp;c. theſe alſo are proper to Chriſt onely.<note place="margin">Morales actiones, quibus le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi morali ſatiisfecit, hae noſtram vitam &amp; mores ad dilectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Det &amp; proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi excita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt.</note> Some are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, theſe laſt are onely imitable; you may take all thus, ſome actions there are of Chriſt which he did as God, ſome as Mediator, ſome as man. The laſt are binding to us to follow: every action of Chriſts is for our inſtruction ſome way or other, and carefull ought we to be to make uſe of it as we ſhould, that ſo none of Chriſts doings do not paſſe by us un-obſerv'd and taken notice of, but that we rightly ponder them,<note place="margin">Omnis Chriſti actio, noſtra eſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio, ſed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, &amp;c.</note> that what is to be admired and wondred at, we may admire and wonder, what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites to praiſe, let them have it, and what is to be imitated, let them be ſet before us, and ſtrive to imitate, and though we cannot act to perfection, yet let us act with affection, and though we cannot do as we ſhould, yet let us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to do it, and though the bodies pace be ſlow, yet may your ſouls be nimble; <hi>Paul</hi> though he could not take hold on, yet did he reach out to thoſe things that were before; And be ſure to ſend love to Chriſt, and let that tell him that all of ſoul and body is following after. And that whatſoever your doings
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38127:9"/> are, yet your deſires are right, for they are to pleaſe him, and glad would you be to be comprehended in that ſaying of the Apoſtle; <hi>As he is, ſo are we in this world:</hi> Blame none for deſiring this, to be like Chriſt; He that is like Chriſt, is very excellent, and the more this likeneſſe is perfected, the nearer is the ſoul to glory. 'Tis an excellent diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of a vertuous ſoul, to ſee it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue good, let the times, places, and people be never ſo bad: and ſo doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it manifeſts a heavenly excellency within, when a ſoul that lives in this wicked &amp; ungodly world, appears in life and converſation heavenly, &amp; ſhines out in a dark world though not with ſo clear a light, as Chriſt, yet is his light &amp; ſhining out like Chriſt; A handſome imitation from ſome, is as pleaſing as great action from others; Lord! thou art not ſtrict to mark what is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, look not on our actings which are imperfect, but Lord conſider what our deſires are, how we deſire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to thee, and help Lord with thy ſpirit; As thou art a loving God, let us be loving chriſtians, as thou art a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Husband, let us be a glorious
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38127:10"/> Spouſe, as thou art a ſoul-pittying-Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, let us be ſoul-obedient Saints; As thou art a fountaine, a Sea, let us be ſtreams, at leaſt drops, and though we are not of ſuch worth as thou O Chriſt,<note place="margin">Quantum unuſquiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſt in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Dei, tantum eſt, &amp;c.</note> yet let us be true coine, and as pounds and pence may have one ſtamp, and the leaſt though not of ſo great a value as the beſt, yet of ſome value; Mark us ſweet Jeſus for thine, though the mark be never ſo ſmall, that ſo what the <hi>Phariſees</hi> meſſengers anſwered thee concerning the Image and ſuperſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the Tribute-money, ſaying, <hi>it is Caeſars,</hi> ſo Lord let the Image and ſtamp upon our ſouls be Chriſts. That ſo our life, our love, our actions may be ſuch as Chriſts, Chriſt and us may have one way, one will, one affection, one mind, our bent and purpoſes the ſame with Jeſus Chriſt: Now the work goes on, now is the mirth, now thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, when all agree in one, when all the Souldiers do like the Captaine, all the ſervants like the maſter, all the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers like the leader, all the members as the head directs, and that there are no diviſions; commands anſwere with obedience, examples ſutable to the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38127:10"/> learners like the teacher, Saints like the Saviour, <hi>As he is, ſo are we, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Obſ:</hi> True Saints are ſuch that are very like Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>There is ſome ſpeciall ſingular thing in Saints that is not in men of the world, there is a ſingular vertue in a Jewell that is not in another ſtone, which makes it eſteemed, there is a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar choice excelling in Saints that makes them ſo extold, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in them that others have not ſeen, nor known,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.10</note> which is manifeſt to them by the ſpirit, they are begotten of God, and ſo come to be like Chriſt as children of one father are like one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: A holy Chriſt the Son of God, and holy Saints children of God,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.11</note> all of one; for which cauſe Chriſt is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to call Saints brethren, and from this brotherhood it is that Chriſt and chriſtians are good friends, that there is ſo much union, peace and affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that they can ſpeak together, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer together, dwell together, feed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, lodge together, and live toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the God of Chriſt, the God of Saints, the Father of Chriſt, the Father
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38127:11"/> of Saints, 'tis the words of Chriſt, the ſoul-delighting words of the Elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Younger, ſent by <hi>Mary</hi> as a meſſage of comfort to the Diſciples,<note place="margin">Ad per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbatos Diſcipulos accurre. <hi>Io. 20.17</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Go to my brethren, and ſay unto them, I aſcend unto my Father and your Father, and to my God and your God.</hi> Here's a cordial, the Diſciples were troubled at their Maſters being crucified, and 'tis likely were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much grieved, Chriſt forgets them not, but ſends them news of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and of his Aſcending into glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that they ſhould aſcend likewiſe, for his Father would not entertain him alone, but them alſo; The inheritance of glory belongs to Saints as well as Chriſt, all Gods children ſhall partake in this kingdom,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.17</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit it ſelf beareth witneſſe with our ſpirit, that we are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Donorum patris cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtis ſunt participes.</note> And if children then heirs, heirs of God, and joynt-heirs with Chriſt. Chriſt had bled freely for them, and his meſſage is ſweet to them, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his ſhould know what glory is provided for them,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.2 Phil. 3.21 Rev. 3, 21</note> and therefore tels them they ſhould be like him, <hi>their vile bodies made like his glorious body, and ſit with him in his Throne,</hi> thoſe that are like him in grace, ſhall be like him in glory, they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38127:11"/> that are partakers with him in bearing the croſſe, ſhall be partakers with him in wearing the crown. Chriſt is faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning his daily for himſelf, and when he hath brought his work to that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection here, that they come unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt and to perfect man,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.13</note> he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them to glory; for the church is heavens nurſery, and as Chriſt ſees fit he draws out thoſe precious plants that are like himſelf, and ſets them with himſelf; Small pieces of gold are look'd to and kept ſafe; if like Chriſt you are well enough ſouls, 'tis no matter who you are unlike; if faſhioned like Chriſt, it matters not how different you are from all others, you are as you ſhould be if like Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The choice work of Chriſt is about ſouls, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> and here (as his skill is required ſo) hee ſhews it, in bringing forth ſo beautifull a piece and rare that was formerly deformed and vile, in making a brat of Satans a Saint, that which was like hell, to be like heaven; that which was moſt ugly, to be like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that is the holy of holies.</p>
            <p>Saints are very like Chriſt, becauſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38127:12"/> whatſoever is found in a Saint as a Saint, it is really one with Chriſt, ſome thing flowing out from Chriſt; In Saints there is <hi>plenitudo vaſis</hi> the fullnes of a veſſell; but in Chriſt is <hi>plenitudo fontis,</hi> a fountain-fullneſſe. The School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſay that Chriſt is as the fire, Chriſtians as things lighted at that fire;<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ignis, &amp; ignita.</note> the fullneſs of the fire is ſuch that light a thouſand torches at it, it is not dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. Fire is not diminiſhed by what is lighted at it, but by the abatement or diminution of the fuel, now Grace in Chriſt cannot be diminiſhed, 'tis not ſubject to any decay; 'tis as he himſelf is, the ſame to day and for ever. Chriſt could not be perfect if ſubject to change; I conceive without offence I may ſay, that as a thing lighted at a fire is like the fire that lighted it, ſo Saints receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grace from Chriſt are like Chriſt from whom they receive that grace;<note place="margin">Joh. 1.16</note> as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are like their Parents, ſo Saints like this everlaſting Father,<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6</note> who is their father.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> Chriſt lives with them, in them, and in this he delights, and all is of like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Like is pleaſed with like, ſo is Chriſt, Saints are like him, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38127:12"/> to be with them. Affections meeting with a right object drawe all after; If the affections be won the whole man is obtain'd ſo tis with Chriſt; where his love is pitched all his excellences will faſten. If Chriſt meet with one in whom his ſoul takes pleaſure, that ſoul cannot doe amiſſe. How kind are men where pleaſed, and what pleaſeth but ſomewhat is ſutable? Somewhat in <hi>David</hi> that lik'd <hi>Jonathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.1</note> cauſ'd him to cloſe with that ſoul-friendſhip, and to continue to the hazarding of his own life, <hi>Davids</hi> friend. Men love to live where they like, and with whom, ſo doth Chriſt, &amp; that is in Saints; they are the perſons he likes, and in them are the places he deſires to make his places of reſidence. Let a man find a place that hee likes, its of force enough to bring him to live there. You need no other argument to draw him thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the mind is of force ſufficient to make him effect what he effects, let the place be in the way to heaven or hel; The mind hath a great hand in the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation or damnation of men;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.6</note> God make our mindes ſpiritual that ſo we may love what is ſpiritual. <hi>A gracious</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:38127:13"/> Chriſt loves gracious ſoules; here is nothing more like him, nor nothing more delightfull to him; his heart is raviſhed with them, exceedingly taken with them, ſo that nothing ſatisfies him but being in them, and by being in them, appears the unity; and by the unity the amity, and by the amity is manifeſted likeneſſe. <hi>Paul</hi> agreed with Saints he being made like them; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not then at Chriſts friendlines with Saints; 'tis but the ſociety of the Bride-groom with the bride, of the head with the members of a man with himſelf. As Chriſts love hath its perfect work on beleeving ſoules, ſo he that is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect worker hath his dwelling there: happy hoſte that hath ſuch a gueſt, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpouſe that hath ſuch a Husband bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſoul that hath ſuch a friend, happy body that hath ſuch a head. The Lord faſhion us like Chriſt, and we doubt not of enioying him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> The thing begotten is like that which begat, now Saints as Saints are begotten of Chriſt, and having Chriſt for their father they are children like him,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.23 Jam. 1.18 <hi>Simile ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerat ſibi ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> time for time, as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> begat a ſon in his own likeneſſe, ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38127:13"/> the ſecond:<note place="margin">Rom 5.19</note> Nature makes us like the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> grace like the ſecond, theres a Certaine likenes betwixt the birth of nature, and the birth of grace. Much of the birth of Saints as Children of Chriſt, may be held out (as in an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem) by the naturall birth God ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much mercy to let thee bee a man ſuch an excellent Creature, That God that hath ſet thee ſo high,<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.6</note> that made thee to have dominion over the ſheep &amp; oxen, the beaſts of the field, the foul of the aire and the fiſh of the Sea, might have made thee the loweſt, the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptibleſt of all theſe, this is not all the mercy yet, heares more, in that thou haſt thy lot in heaven amongſt Saints in the good land, where the goſpell ſhines and wherein God in mercy dwels. It is a poor buſineſſe for all this to brag of theſe things, unleſſe thou art born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>again of the ſpirit, for it is the new birth that makes thee inheritour of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things of Chriſt. Once born is not enough, <hi>Judas</hi> had that but not the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the execellent name of Chriſtians of right is by the ſecond birth. Thou maieſt by thy firſt birth be a play-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low with Saints, as children meanly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38127:14"/> deſcended may be with the children of Nobles, yet not Noble nor ſhare in the inheritance or titles of honour: The five fooliſh Virgins were companions a while with the wiſe,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> but at length ſeparated, ſo may carnall men, men once borne with Saints, men twice borne; but God wil find them out when he ſeparates the precious from the vile, when he makes up his jewels: and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the wheat into his barne, then it will little advantage a ſoul that it hath had a good name when 'tis found with a bad ſoul,<note place="margin">Quid tibi prodeſt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari quod non es.</note> that it hath eat and drunke with the Saints, when it ſhall enjoy no inheritance with them, but be ſhut out into outer darkneſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. 22.13,</hi> Quid tibi prodeſt iſta memoria, ſi ubi es, torquris, et ubi non es, lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris? <hi>Cor. 15.21.22.</hi>
               </note> It may be thou maieſt leave ſomewhat behinde thee, that Carnall men may commend thee for, what comfort is this if you ſhould be in the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone, in a word, the firſt birth let it be never ſo perfect ſets us but in a miſerable world, higher it cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance. Neither King nor Noble happy by natures birth; tis the ſecond birth gives perfection.</p>
            <p>By this ſouls are very holy, what Conceptions are in ſoules by Chriſt,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38127:14"/> they are very like Chriſt himſelf, holy;<note place="margin">Spiritus Jeſus, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſanctus, ſpiritus rectus, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis. &amp;c.</note> ſpirituall, heavenly. The ſeed of man may corrupt: but not the ſeed of God, where he caſts his grace there will be growth and fruit ſutable; wheat brings forth wheat; and barly brings forth barly; every ſeed a body like it ſelf; ſo doth Chriſt. There are no more holy, heavenly, ſpirituall children then they that have the Father of Heaven theirs, An everlaſting father begets everlaſting children a holy father holy children, Saints. 2. By this they are bleſſed, they that are begotten of bleſſed Chriſt, are bleſſe ſoules, a happy man may have children, and yet they may not be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, a good man may have bad children, but tis not ſo with Chriſt, all Chriſts children are Good, all his offſpring according to the ſpirit happy. If he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get <hi>Paul,</hi> he ſhall have occaſion enough to magnifie his birth: laying aſide the firſt birth, he boſts not of that: it is the ſecond rejoyeth his heart: al bleſſed pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges came by the ſecond, the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the ſecond are but as dung and droſſe. 3. By this they are preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, a precious Chriſt begetting cauſeth precious ſoules begotten. The Kings
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38127:15"/> daughter is glorious,<note place="margin">Pſ. 45.13</note> all glorious, every limbe glorious, within and without glorious,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.27</note> as of Chriſt without ſpot or wrinckle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col. 1.22</hi> Quatenus conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Chriſto, non ſolum ſine macu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la eſt, ſed infinito decoro ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornata, &amp;c.</note> or any thing like it, holy, unblamable, and unreproveable: the heart pure, upright, ſanctified through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, the hands cleane, the life faultleſſe, without defilement, walking in all gods waies blameleſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe expreſſions as they have relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Chriſtians, are to be underſtood of the righteouſnes of Chriſtians, as they are conſidered under the Covenant of grace and of the Goſpel, not of legal perfection but of an Evangelical inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie and uprightneſſe, not as they are in themſelves, but as in Chriſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is full of Love, peace, goodnes; ſo are Saints his children, children en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed with love, peace, goodneſs. Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taken out of a fountain, relliſheth like that in the fountain, fruit is ſut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the tree? 'Tis ſo with Saints, they are ſtreames of a good fountain, they are fruit of a precious tree. Fruit of life, growing on the tree of life, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtreames begun, and nouriſhed by a living fountain. A loving Chriſt brings
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38127:15"/> forth loving children, Chriſt the Prince of peace, ſons and daughters of peace; Chriſt that is all good conceives to his goodneſs.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They that are born of Chriſt affect what is good, what is heavenly. The birth of Creatures is maintain'd with ſuch food as he that begat it is, A mans birth with mans food, drought will ſtarve it. Earthly things nouriſheth not a heavenly birth, the world is a ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother that will ſtarve it, they are the breſts of Chriſts Conſolations (that as it deſires) muſt nouriſh it; 'Tis bread of life, and water of life, and food of life that it muſt have; Wiſdoms food &amp; feaſts, feed and banquet wiſdomes chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Every Morſel, Saints eat that nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth them, muſt have ſomewhat of Chriſt, he is living food for living ſouls. I am (ſaith Chriſt) that bread of life: <hi>He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 6.</note> 
               <hi>dwelleth in me, and I in him;</hi> He that eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and drinketh him ſhall live for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Souls, conſider what food you feed on; Creatures nature appears much in the nouriſhing: they deſire, and eat; A beaſt is pleaſed, if it may have beaſts food; A man if mans food, ſo hear.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38127:16"/> The firſt Adams children are contented with the worlds food, give them world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things they are pleaſed, if the world will give them plenty from her Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, they look not after any other; But the ſecond Adams children are not thus pleaſed, they muſt have ſomewhat from heaven, they will bleſſe God for loaves, but they will not be quiet with them, if they have not ſomewhat elſe, they have ſouls alſo to care for, theſe muſt be ſatisfied, or all is not well with them; Hungry ſouls are reſtleſs, Chriſt ſhall not be unſought unto till they are fild. I need not bid you examine your ſelves, what diet pleaſeth you, you are pleaſed as you are; If worldly, with worldly things; if heavenly, with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things. I could tell what preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing would pleaſe you all, but I forbear; I am ſure, no preaching pleaſeth Saints but the preaching of Chriſt, God in mercy give all you that have been born but once, one birth more, a ſecond birth; then will you long for the food that nouriſheth you to everlaſting life.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> True Saints are very like Chriſt, for Chriſt is known by them, the virtues, graces, ſweetneſs, wholeſomneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:38127:16"/> that is in Saints, and which they hold out in their converſation, ſets out in ſome ſort Chriſt. A gracious man hath much of Chriſt; whatſoever truly names him gracious, is Chriſt. Books bear their names from what is in them; And houſes and lands (uſually) from thoſe that poſſeſſe them. We may gueſſe what the fountain is by taſting of the ſtream, what the book is by the title. If ſuch and ſo much of the delicateneſs of Chriſt be in earthen veſſels, what is in glory it ſelf? if poor man be of ſo much worth that hath but one ſmal drop of this Ocean in him, what is the Sea it ſelf worth? A man may conceive a Rocke of Pearle to be of a great value, when a ſmal duſt is ſo much worth. True Saints though they have but little of Chriſt, yet may it lead you to this, that if Chriſt in a creature be ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and his graces make them lovely, doubtleſs, he as in himſelf is exceeding eminent and lovely. Saints at moſt are but as it were the picture, or image, now if the Image be admired, much more the perſon that is repreſented. An Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age may be like the ſubſtance, ſo a Saint like Chriſt. Chriſt is known other
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38127:17"/> waies, yet in ſome meaſure this way, by Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe: </seg>
               </label> Chriſtians, you deſire now to know who are truly godly, 'tis an age of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, all is not gold that gliſters, there are falſe wares, falſe men, and there are falſe chriſtians, there are ſome that have a name,<note place="margin">2 Ep. Ioh. 6. <hi>Multi ſunt in mundo impoſtores.</hi> Matth. 24.24.25.26.</note> they live but are dead, there are many deceivers in the world, the world is full of ſoul-cheats, hardly any place free. The time is fully come, Chriſt propheſied of, there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſigns and wonders: in ſo much that (if it were poſſible) they ſhall deceive the very Elect. Behold, I have told you before. Wherefore if they ſhall ſay unto you, <hi>Behold, he is in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, go not forth: Behold, he is in the ſecret-chambers, believe it not;</hi> Such Impoſtours are deceitfull,<note place="margin">Matth. 24.5.</note> and ſhall deceive many, beware you. They ſhall uſe the name of Chriſt, as their colour or pretence, and ſuch are likely (unleſſe there be great heed taken) to deceive; Sea-men are ſpoiled by Pyrats, that hang out their own colours,<note place="margin">Prov. 7.14.</note> that harlot was winning that pretended honeſty; Souls, know Gods Merchants are vending as good
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38127:17"/> Merchandize now as ever the world had held out, and the devils as bad, he will keep market where God doth, he hath his cheats to vend, where God hath his truths. It is too hard a labour for me to find all the deceits that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, what lies in the heart of one man is not known;<note place="margin">Ierem. 17.9.</note> the bottom can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſearch'd, every heart hath its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, and they are many, the world is full, the devil hath many large ſhops and many wares. I ſhall give you the Evangeliſts counſel: <hi>Look to your ſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Ep. Ioh. 8.</note> were you going to a fair, and one ſhould ſay to you, look to your purſes, there are many cut-purſes and cheats, how cautious would you be; Take heed of your ſouls Chriſtians, 'tis for them Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan goes about, he hath what he aimes at if he gets them, and he never hath his aime till he hath them; But it is men, not things, that I have in hand, you ſay you cannot tell who to truſt, and I ſay ſo too. Chriſt can diſcover all, the Lord haſten this work, he can find out the man without the wedding Garment though the Gueſts perceive him not,<note place="margin">Matth, 22.11.</note> he can ſhew you which are the fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, which the wiſe, though they lie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38127:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:38127:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:38127:19"/> for a whiles undiſcerned. 'Tis uſual with men to think God ſuch as themſelves;<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.21.</note> no wonder then that they take them for Saints that are like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Too too many go hand in hand to deſtruction. Your Carnal worldly men they take none to be godly but themſelves, and ſuch as they are that are good Husbands, and correſpond with the world, doing (as they ſay) no man wrong, paying every man his own, no Saints to them but theſe: ſo people that are got into ſuch a form of worſhip, they look upon none in Zion, but they that do as they do, all others are in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.</hi> Many will not pray nor performe any duty of Religion with thoſe that are not of their opinion; Oh ſtrange! If this be not to have the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt with reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, what is? Could the Apoſtle eſteem highly of thoſe that were gracious, and ſhal not we, whether they were by nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> whether circumciſed, or not circumciſed: if holy Souls pray, you may diſcern where Chriſt dwels, (they are true ſoules) love ſuch, Chriſt is holy, they that have him are holy, Chriſt is truth, they have truth tha
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38127:19"/> have him, Chriſt is mercifull, ſo are they that are Chriſts; Truſt not to my words, you may be deceiv'd, and ſo may I; yet I ſhall give you ſome hint of Saints that are ſo like Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There are ſome that are very uſeful ſouls, theſe are like Chriſt; you know how uſeful Chriſt is.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The prayers of Chriſt are uſefull, ſo are the prayers of Saints: Chriſt was much in prayer for the Churches good,<note place="margin">Pſal. 127.6.</note> ſo are Saints. Jeruſalem is preferred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their chiefe joy, <hi>Nehemiah, Daniell, Ezekiell, David,</hi> were praying ſoules, they were alwaies mindfull of the church, and ſo were others that were gratious. Saints are very like Chriſt in this, he prayed for his very enemies, ſo do they; he prayed for the Lords ſtrength to ſtrengthen his church, ſo do they;<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.15.</note> he prayed his church might be kept from the evil of the world, Saints have this among their petitions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The company of Chriſt is uſeful. How uſefull was Chriſt when in the fleſh to many diſtreſſed ſouls? what place came he unto that he did not do ſome good in? how bleſſed are they that have his preſence now, to cheere them, heale
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38127:20"/> them, helpe them according to their ſeverall needs; are not Saints thus to their power? do they not exerciſe the gift given them for others good? 'Tis a bleſſed condition, (I aſſure you a Saint that knows beſt how to judge thinks it ſo) to live in ſuch places where it may have the company of thoſe that are truly godly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt is ſo uſeful that he holds out all he hath to Saints, what he poſſeſſeth in grace or glory 'tis preſented to ſouls, all is ready to do them good. Heres liberality, 'tis ſo with thoſe that are Chriſts, they think nothing too dear to be ſpent for their brethrens good, a free Chriſt,<note place="margin">Act. 3.32, 34.</note> and free Saints, ready to ſell and part withall, to help the neceſſities of fellow-members. The hand will not keepe money in it when the foot or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts need it; the foot will not fit ſtill when the body requires 'its help. There is a naturall helping amongſt members, ſo amongſt Saints. There are few like Chriſt in this, indeed few that are like him all; They are more like the devill then Chriſt, they put out all they have to do miſchiefe, body, Eſtate, all goes if they thinke they may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38127:20"/> Saints; let them buy hell, they may have time enough to complain of their bargain; They that are ſo unlike Chriſt and Saints here, ſhall have ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table company, but it ſhall be neither Chriſt nor any of his holy ones. The Lord grant you grace that in this you may imitate Chriſt and be like him, in uſing what you have ſo for him &amp; his, that you may give up an account of your ſtewardſhip with joy and not with griefe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some are very pittiful ſouls, they are pittifull from a Principle of grace, theſe are like Chriſt. If they ſee a poor creature in an ignorant ſottiſh ſtate, how do they bemoan him, take all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities poſſible to bring him to the knowledge of the truth?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia eſt vicina mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeriae.</hi> Sen. l. 2. de Clem.</note> A merciful man ſtrives to be Neighbour to him that is in need, and who more then the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant? <hi>Paul</hi> was very pittiful affected this way, ſo are they that are like Chriſt, compaſſionate to their bodily needs; they ſtrive to be merciful as their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly father is merciful. They are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent for ſhewing pitty that are Chriſts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They commiſerate the wilful, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38127:21"/> ſtrive to bring them to obedience, they have learned Chriſts language, crying out, why wil you die O obſtinate ſouls? why will you croſſe Chriſt and at length bring an eternall curſe upon your ſelves?<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.14.</note> they have ſuch Yearning bowells after them, that it many times drawes teares from them. They may be ill dealt withal, and have many a mock and jeere and ſuffering for their good will, yet this beates them not off, it makes them not deſiſt, but hold out, with Chriſt ſeeking their Good that cannot endure them;<note place="margin">Iſa. 65.23.</note> You may ſee how Chriſt was, ſerved yet what he did; I ſtretched out my hands all the day, to a rebellious people: a people that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh me to anger continually to my very face: 'Tis ſo with many Saints, do not many preach the word to ſuch that are deadly adverſaries to them, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſeth them to the very face, nay, in the very time they are perſwading them,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.15. Act. 7.57. <hi>Summa mundi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitudo.</hi>
               </note> &amp; the more a Saints ſpirit in pitty is for their good, the more are their ſpirits in rage againſt Saints to their hurt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They have yearnings of ſoule after ſuch that deviate from truth that goe aſtray in the wildernes of ſin, ſtriving to reclaime them, and to bring them
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38127:21"/> into the way of the Lord, to walke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards holynes,<note place="margin">Act. 17.23</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> was employ'd in ſuch a buſines as this at <hi>Athens</hi> amonſt a people that were wandering after an unknowne God, that went they knew not whither,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.4.</note> that worſhipped they knew not what. As a man lookes after a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering beaſt to bring it home, ſo doth Chriſt a wandering ſoul; and this is part of the employment of ſuch that can ſay, <hi>As he is, ſo are we in this world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 34.6, 7, 8, 9.</note> Chriſt is highly diſpleaſed with ſuch that ſhould looke after ſcattered ſoules, and are negligent, they walke contrary to him; but ſuch pleaſe him that are painfull in preſerving thoſe are his, that undertake any employment for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of ſoules from error to truth, from out of the Devils common to Chriſts ſold. They are deare friends to Chriſt, that to their utmoſt are helpful to the purchaſed poſſeſſion of Chriſt: you that are good ſervants to Chriſt, you ſhall find him a good Maſter to you: be like him in action, and he will make you like himſelfe in the reward, he that works in his vineyard ſhall have faire wages. Bleſſed are you that now ſerve not your ſelves but the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; this buſines will make Chriſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38127:22"/> honour you; your ſtriving to reclaime ſuch that wander from the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord:<note place="margin">Dan. 12.3.</note> They that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament: and they that turne many to righteouſneſſe, as the ſtarres for ever and ever. God will honour them that ſtrive to ſave others.<note place="margin">Jam. 5.20.</note> How like Chriſt are they that ſtrive to convert a ſinner from the error of his way, and to ſave a ſoul from death? Is not ſuch work Chriſts worke? do not they follow him that works thus? When Chriſt works in us for making us like him, we will worke abroad to bring ſoules unto him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They loath ſinne, they that are like Chriſt, they deteſt and abominate what Chriſt deteſts. Sin is a devil (and who can abid him unleſſe wretches that are like him.) Sin will eat up a ſoul; can any unleſſe a mad-man love that which will utterly undoe him? Sinne brings plagues upon a mans ſelfe and all he hath, entertain not a gueſt that hath ſuch ill attendants, thou canſt not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace ſin but thou muſt wound Chriſt: wilt thou ſhew ſo much hard-heartednes as to wound him that hath ſuffered ſo much already,<note place="margin">Iſa. 52.14.</note> yea ſuch ſufferings, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any ſuffered beſides him, beſides you cannot
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38127:22"/> ſinne againſt Chriſt but you muſt hurt your ſelves, yea your beſt part,<note place="margin">Pro. 8.36.</note> your ſouls, but to caſt ſuch weeds aſide and to ſpeak of men and practiſes fiting the place and time, and that is Saints &amp; their behaviour in this particular towards ſin, they abhorre ſin upon the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and grounds that Jeſus Chriſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horres it, 'tis indeed Chriſt in them that makes them diſlike it if their diſlike be ſuch as it ſhould be, there are ſoules that may have ſome diſlike of ſin, yet they may not with a Saints ſpirit loath it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some there are that ſtand aloofe from ſin when it allures, becauſe ſhould they yeeld, it may cauſe ſome diſgrace to them, it may make ſome caſt them off that now they have favour withall, and whoſe favour it may be is more benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial for preſent then their ſin can be, they are ſollicited unto. Theſe deſerve no thankes from God, for love to God makes them not diſlike ſin, 'tis the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of ſome reputation and credit amongſt men that for preſent reſtrains them. They ſay not, I have receiv'd mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from Chriſt, how can I ſin againſt him that hath been ſo good to me? but I have a reaſon of mine own, ſaith the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38127:23"/> carnal ſoule, and therefore I may doe this or that, not but that he loves the ſin, but it ſtands not with his end for preſent to meddle with it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some are kept off from ſin as the dog from the bone with the cudgel, the feare of the Law deters them, faine they would be doing but then they feare ſuffering, they thinke it might be beneficiall to ſteale, but they like not hanging, the money might help them but the halter would hurt them; Chriſt is not beholding to theſe nor to any ſuch, for love to him prevailes not with them;<note place="margin">Mat. 14.5.</note> theſe are kept from evil as <hi>Herod</hi> at firſt from killing <hi>John</hi> for feare of the people,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.2.</note> &amp; as the Chief Prieſts &amp; Scribes from killing Jeſus, or the Captain and Officers from offering violence to the Apoſtles.<note place="margin">Act. 5.26.</note> That many are not more vile wee may thanke their feare of the Law, not their love nor likeneſſe to Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some are kept from ſome ſins for fear of hell; Hell is not ſeen, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not much feard, men think ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of hell, take heed you never know it, this place of Torments is not much conſidered of now, or if it be, men think
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38127:23"/> they are far enough from it and may eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape. If love to Chriſt keepe not from ſin, fear of hell will not; 'tis the mercies of Chriſt that <hi>Paul</hi> preſents as a bait to allure to holineſſe, and drawe men off from the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 12.1</hi> — Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem miſerecor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae Dei debere no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis eſſe ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulum ad vitam Deo pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem tranſigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</note> mercies are very invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, eſpecially the mercies of Chriſt that are ſuch ſweet &amp; precious mercies, <hi>mercies</hi> that had never any like <hi>them,</hi> the world had never ſuch another in it for mercy as Chriſt. Mercies drawe Saints to abhorre evill, and as God ſhall call you to be Saints, you will do likewiſe. Sin is offence to Chriſt and goodneſſe is pleaſing to him. Saints (are acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him and) know it and ſtrive it ſhould be ſo to them, Chriſt and inſide Chriſtians, have but one object of their love &amp; but one of their hatred, viz: <hi>good</hi> and all good, and that they effect toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; evill and all evill and that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject a like, you may conceive of ſuch to be Saints that go ſo right with Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Saints indeed, (ſoules like Chriſt they are ſuch that aime at the glory of God) in all their undertakings, it was Chriſts meat and drinke to do the will of his father, ſo 'tis theirs that are Chriſts, if men will be pleaſ'd ſeeing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38127:24"/> them in Gods buſineſſe they rejoyce but if they will not, they nevertheleſſe continue doing; There was a Gallant courage in Chriſt to glorify his Father, ſo is there in Saints, they will honour God if they die in the action,<note place="margin">Act. 5.19.</note> they if oppos'd durſt bidt heir oppoſers judge whether it be better to obey God or man, he acts right that bids his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my be judge of his doings: if any ſpy faults, enemies will. Saints are for pleaſing God, thats their aime, they are company for ſuch whoſe journey is heaven-ward; Chriſt is gone before, they follow after. He goes faſteſt to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that goes on moſt ſpeedily in Gods worke, that, as it tends to Gods glory, ſo to the actors glory. A ſoul will ſoone be glorified it ſelfe, that glorifies God; they that are for God, ſhall be with God; heavenly work is recompens'd with good wayes; Chriſt did his work, is entred into his joy, doe yours and enter alſo, like doers ſhall have like pay.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Chriſt is for fellowſhip and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with his people,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note> (where two or three are gathered together in his name, there he is, in the midſt of them)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38127:24"/> ſo Saints the friends of Chriſt deſire fellowſhip with thoſe that are Chriſts: chriſtians, this Leſſon hath not been well learn'd of late, outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances like our ſelves, (tis feard) have drawne us many times more then Chriſt in Spirit dwelling in ſouls. That part of Arethmeticke diviſion hath beene in uſe too much, at leaſt Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration too little, we ſhould be more like Chriſt were we more for ſociety, I meane with Saints. Davids Spirit was gratious and was much affected with ſuch company, if like Chriſt ſociable, but 'tis with Saints.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Chriſt delights to ſee men holy, embracing truth, in this Saints are like Chriſt. Saint <hi>John</hi> rejoyced great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he found the children of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Lady walking in truth,<note place="margin">Epiſt. Ioh. 2.4</note> ſo this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe was pleaſing to <hi>Paul.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.3, 4.</note> We give thanks to God, and the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, praying alwayes for you, ſince we heard of your faith in Chriſt Jeſus, &amp; of the love which ye have to all the Saints. As he rejoyced to ſee this amongſt the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> for it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to ſee others followers of the Lord,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.6</note> and embracing that truth which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38127:25"/> the churches of God embraced,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.14.</note> to the exceeding growth of faith, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding of charity each towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.3.</note> They that were holy amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> rejoyced at the <hi>Gentiles</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. And at this day there is no greater joy to Saints then to hear of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers turning to the truth, and living holily. That which makes carnal men diſpleaſ'd, which is newneſſe of life, pleaſeth thoſe that have received of the ſame life.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 33</note>7. Jeſus Chriſt hates ſin in every one, yet no mans perſon, he pitties their perſons, <hi>Why will you die O houſe of Iſrael?</hi> He loath'd <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ſin, yet he wept o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the city as pittying the people, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing through foreſeeing of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that was coming towards them', and did afterwards befal them; They that are like Chriſt are thus qualified, they hate ſin in all men, yet hate not the perſons of any, no, not of their deadly enemies, but with <hi>Stephen</hi> they can deſire eternal life, for thoſe, that will not let them enjoy a temporal life, a crown for their enemies, that hale them to the croſſe; There's much of the image of Chriſt in thoſe that to the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38127:25"/> utmoſt do good to the men, whoſe ſins they hate; And though they ſeek the death of their ſin, yet deſire life, the life of Chriſt for their ſouls. Chriſt ſhewed man moſt mercy, when he ſhewed ſinne none; he kill'd ſin, and quickn'd man; A man may be merciful to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, yet ſtrive to be a ſlaughter-man to his ſin: They muſt needs be like Chriſt, that from a gratious pitty are helpful to others, and omit no meanes to do them any kindneſſe, furthering the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their ſouls, and good of their bodies, helping them in any thing, or way but what is ſinful; 'Tis the calling of Saints to do good, yea to all, you have none of a more free ſpirit then they, they go up and down on this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, 'tis the errand that Chriſt ſends them on; Like Maſter, like Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, all good, and their actions like themſelves: The maſter cannot erre, the ſervants may, but they ſhall be ſet right again; Theſe are no cheats that do good to all, as much as poſſible they may, harm none, no not enemies; render to none evill for evil, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe bleſſing.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Saints are very much like Chriſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:38127:26"/> in that they are couragious ſouls, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious in what is good, not bad, ſome men have too much courage in an evil way, but to what is good they have no heart. 'Tis not ſo with the children of God, they die rather then yield to any baſeneſſe, ſhall ſuch a one as I flie? a gallant ſpeech of a noble ſoul,<note place="margin">Neh. 6.11.</note> of one that believed God had given command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſave him,;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 71.3. Salvum me facias ab inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis meis.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel</hi> would not omit his duty, though he knew the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons den was to be his puniſhment. God ſhould have his honour whatſoever he ſuffered; The three children feared not the wrath of the King, nor the fiery Furnace; God ſhould not be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by them, they would die rather. Tyrants may kill Saints but not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer them. Chriſt was ſlaine but not overcome, ſo it may be with thoſe are Chriſts; That's good mettal will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the fire; a good Ship that holds ſound and firm in all ſtorms; good cloth that ſhrinks not in wetting; wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded colours that fade not; brave ſouls that nothing can daunt, diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, or turn from the truth; one of theſe is better then a thouſand, that have great words, but when hardſhip
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38127:26"/> comes to be undergone prove low and weake; he's a friend that owns a man in need, and in a ſtrait; he's a Saint that from inward grace is made ſo cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious that nothing ſhall ſeparate him as from the love of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.7</note> ſo from the worke of Chriſt. The Mettall of a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier is tried in the Battel, the ſpirit of a Chriſtian in times of oppoſition.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Chriſt is all for drawing ſouls to himſelf;<note place="margin">Joh. 12.32</note> if he be lifted up from the earth he will draw men to him, he is not a ſcatterer, but a gatherer, I mean of ſouls. His buſineſſe is to ſeeke and to ſave, to find and preſerve, he woes, and willing he is to marry ſoules, that they might be his for ever, chriſtians in this are ſpirited like Chriſt, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to drive a trade for Chriſts gain, they are for their maſters profit, they love Chriſt, &amp; find exceeding benefit by him, and they think others ſhould love him alſo. Pretious Chriſt is pretious to them, and faine would they have him ſo to others. They have an enlarg'd heart, and an open mouth crying to ſouls, oh! love the Lord all ye people, turne in hither ſouls, come, buy wine, and milke without noney, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38127:27"/> price, we have found Excellent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment from Chriſt, come; he will ſhew you kindneſſe; good ſoules will not conceale the bountifull mercy of the Lord,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 7.9.</note> if they neglect to publiſh his goodneſs, they wil ſay as the Lepers, we do not well to hold our peace; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they cannot but make mention of the name of the Lord. Chriſtians are not tongue-tied in ſetting out Chriſts worth, they may be in ſpeaking of themſelves; ſound and Gratious. Souls are ſparing in ſpeaking things tending to their own praiſe, but when occaſion is offered to ſet out any thing for the honour of their Saviour, they want no words at leaſt no will, to inlarge themſelves on ſuch a theame. You people that would not be deceiv'd in owning thoſe that are right, that are afraid of a Devil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing as an Angel of light, that faine would have a chriſtian indeed your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, ſuch ſouls are very likely to fit you, that are induſtrious in enlarging Chriſts dominions, and are joyful when ſoules come in apace to Chriſt, for true Saints would have all men ſavd and come to the knowledge of the truth.</p>
            <p>Chriſtians, whatſoever I have ſaid of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38127:27"/> this uſe. I muſt yet wiſh you to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware. Pickpockets will be amongſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men, cheaters amongſt juſt dealers, and if the ſons of men preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before God Satan is ready to be amongſt them. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> Secondly There may be an uſe of information given out; the Doctrine will affor'd it, and indeed the times conſider'd, it may be ſeaſonable and it manifeſteth the ground and riſe of perſecution againſt Saints; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever there are godly ſoules be ſure there is ſome ſtir;<note place="margin">Iſ. 50.15.</note> there is ſome fire a Kindling. He that departs from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity makes himſelf a pray, hee's the but at which all the ſhooting is, all the hooting is at him. We hear of <hi>Pauls</hi> perſecuting, but not of being perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the time he walked according to the courſe of the world: but Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reveal'd in him, wrath is revealed againſt him, hee being for Chriſt; enemies of Chriſt ſet againſt him in every place:<note place="margin">Act. 20 23.</note> The more like Chriſt any is, and the more they own him and follow him, the more is the trouble that riſeth againſt them: the ſea-waves give the greateſt daſh againſt what op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſeth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38127:28"/> them. The wind roareth moſt amongſt thoſe trees that tis ſtifly oppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, all wicked people rage againſt ſuch that any may hinder them in their wickedneſſe. I dare challenge people in any city Country or village, that if they will ſpeak truth, that they that are moſt Godly amongſt them, are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to moſt ſlanders,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> reproaches, and wrongs. I know wicked men have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences for what they do againſt Saints: So had the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt Chriſt.<note place="margin">Jo. 18.30</note> They tell <hi>Pilate,</hi> if he were not a malefactour, they would not have delivered him up unto him; <hi>Chriſt</hi> might have ſaid to them as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> are ye wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of receiving ſo many benefits by one man? <hi>Paul</hi> had many grevious faults laid to his charge, as turning the world upſide downe,<note place="margin">Act. 27.6.</note> ſetting all out of order, his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſpake as if all had been well, had it not been for him and ſuch as he were: This <hi>Paul</hi> was a peſtilent fellow, a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of ſedition all the world over,<note place="margin">Act. 14.5.</note> high crimes to be accuſ'd of, and why was this? becauſe Godly, that was the main thing that troubled Satans ſlaves. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pnen</hi> is accuſ'd for blaſphemy &amp; what was his blaſphemy?<note place="margin">Act. 6.14.</note> part is he ſhould ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38127:28"/> the holy place and the law, and <hi>That Jeſus of Nazareth ſhall deſtroy this place and change the cuſtomes which Moſes deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us.</hi> Falſe witneſſes, and men ſuborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed laid this in againſt him; Knowing that it would mightily incenſe the people to hear of loſing their cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. Theſe carnall cuſtomes are ſo dear to carnall men that they are all in a rage if they heare any thing of loſing them. Let Goſpel go and Goſpell own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers periſh, they care not, if they may keep their cuſtomes. It was a cuſtome to have this and that: I count it not worth the naming what many contend about and perſecute the Saints for. I could experimentally ſpeak in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular but I forbear; Doubtleſſe the ſpirit of men is in every age ſpit out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt truth, &amp; they that now perſecute Saints would perſecute Chriſt as really as ever the <hi>Jews</hi> did, were his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance now in fleſh as then. Suppoſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> would not obſerve Chriſtmas as the Popiſh generation cals it, ſuppoſe he would not read over a Dead corps, ſuppoſe he would not give the Lords. Supper to any but holy and godly ſouls ſhutting out the covetous, ignorant,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38127:29"/> ſwearer, drunkard, reviler, unclean perſon &amp;c. What would the world ſay of him? I ſpeake low to your capacity, I might ſpeake higher to men in higher place, &amp; fully clear it, why <hi>good</hi> men are ſo perſecuted; But hear Chriſt himſelf, <hi>I have given them thy word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>the world hath hated them, becauſe they are not of the world, as I am not of the world.</hi> See the cleaving to the word what it meets withal, it was not having the word in their houſes or hand made them hated, but in heart and life, and walking contrary to the courſe of the world, for in body they were in the world, but in converſation they were averſe to the world: in a word they through grace received did endeavour to glorifie the God of all grace, this was fault enough, for all that wil live godly muſt ſuffer tribulation. Chriſt was perſecuted ſo ſhal they be that are Chriſts,<note place="margin">Cum ipſo in anguſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ia. <hi>Mat. 18.8.</hi> O bone Jeſu, qic ure, hic percu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te; ut par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo-</note> thornes and briers are in the way to heaven, and they will ſcratch. Be not diſmaid, Chriſt is gone thorow and he will help you, you were better goe to heaven in a torn skin then to hell in a whole; Every skar that a Chriſtian wears for Chriſts ſake, is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens badge, be not aſhamed of them, if
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:38127:29"/> you be found in Chriſts livery, you will be received into bliſſe.<note place="margin">Erigat ſeſe fidelis anima &amp; parata ſibi conſideret bona.</note> Thinke of this you ſouls of honour, if you ſuffer with Chriſt you ſhall reign in glory with him; ponder of the glory when you are under the croſſe, it may quicken your almoſt tir'd ſpirits; I wiſh you may hold out in the ſuffering, and then I queſtion not your glory; That you faint not nor be weary, the Lord grant that your hearts frame may be chang'd from what it is by nature, and turn'd into a Chriſts frame what it ſhould be by grace, your corrupt mind, into a pure mind; paſſion, turn'd into patience, pride, into meekneſſe, loftineſſe, into lowlineſſe, weakneſſe, into ſtrength, fearfulneſſe, into courage; that ſo you may undauntedly undergo ſufferings. Souls, I wiſh you well, howſoever you deal with me, I pray for you, and hope I ſhall; that God would count you worthy to ſuffer for his ſake, which you ſhall certainly undergo in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure if Godly. The Devils birders are abroad, 'tis the beſt birds they aime at,<note place="margin">Quis nori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Daemonis aſtus?</note> his nets are laid, he cares not for catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dogs, 'tis heart, 'tis a precious diſh in hell; yet be of good cheer ſouls, if
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38127:30"/> you are truly good, Satan ſhall have none of you, you are reſerv'd for the maſters uſe, he hath need of you and will have you. Chriſtians, the world is full of Blackmores, I mean black ſouls, if any white ſoul, <hi>viz.</hi> a gracious Saint appear, he's wonder'd at. Let the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wonder and hate,<note place="margin">Deus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator certantium &amp; corona vincenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> Chriſt obſerves and loves all that are his, and will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve every haire, be of good comfort keep this pretious ſoul-promiſe in your hearts. Suffering Saints, Chriſt brought it forth for you;<note place="margin">Mat. 5.11, 12.</note> bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my ſake; (ſaith Chriſt) rejoyce and bee exceeding glad; for great is your reward in heaven: for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets, which were before you. So chriſtians that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, you are not the firſt, there are ſome ſufferers before, follow on there is a crown in readines for you, and I would it were on your heads. I hope it will be, and then will you appeare more cleerly like Chriſt, for a crowned Chriſt and crowned Saints are very like each other.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> I ſhall ſouls, put you to it now, in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38127:30"/> deſiring you to conſider who you are like,<note place="margin">Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni nomen fruſtra ille ſorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, qui Chriſtum minime imitatur.</note> many go for Chriſts people that are never a whit like him, neither fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned like him within nor without; neither in ſpeech, nor ſhape like him; nor yet in word nor converſation. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are more like Satan, and were it not for the name of chriſtians, you would not know them ſcarcely from Devils, I am ſure not from heathen. Their language ſpeaks them not of the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> nor of Chriſts flock, but rather Goates and aliens from, if not enemies to Chriſt. Earthly they are and not heavenly, he that is of the earth is earthly and ſpeaketh of the earth.<note place="margin">Joh. 3.13.</note> As ducklings have alwaies their bils in the mud, ſwine their noſes in the mire, every thing tends to what likes him, ſo carnal men. Travaile upon the way and you ſhall find how familiar people of like diſpoſitions are, gratious men for gracious company and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, worldly and carnal men abhor ſuch company and communication, but if thry meet with ſuch as are carnal, then they are pleas'd. Homogeneal things eaſily cloſe, water will run with water in the ſame channel, dogs will
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38127:31"/> play with dogs, &amp; wolves with wolves, try men by their company; you may find a ſheep amongſt wolves, 'tis rare, unleſſe they prey, to devour; Souls I will not judge you, you have a judge within you, bring the queſtion you would have decided before him, if you will hear he will ſpeak to the buſineſſe, the ſentence ſhall be impartial, it is conſcience properly to ſay the truth be it for a man or againſt him; Ask con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, how like Chriſt? ask conſcience, whether ſuch as you be are Saints? ask conſcience, whether heavens glory have ſuch as you? ask conſcience whether you are skil'd in Scripture, and whether you walk according to the word? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be company for Chriſt? do not miſunderſtand conſcience, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hearken to ſomething elſe that is not conſcience. Well dear friends, I muſt haſten; I will put but one Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatory to you, and end this Uſe; here are many people in this pariſh, ſome love the truth, others hate it, ſome are religious, ſome profane, ſome zealous, ſome but moral; who of theſe do you moſt affect? whoſe houſes do you moſt frequent? whoſe ſoſciety is your delight? I know you can tell, I will
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38127:31"/> conclude nothing: I know what I might, what I could ſay, but I forbear. Lovers ſee ſomewhat in the object that delights the affection, ſomething that pleaſeth them, I can gueſſe what the man is if I am ſure what he loves,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Qualis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor tuus, talis ipſe es.</p>
                  <p>Amans &amp; res amata fiunt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</p>
                  <p>Si divina diligis ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficieris di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus.</p>
               </note> for the affection pitcheth upon ſomewhat ſutable; he hath a heavenly heart that loves heavenly things, he may be ſaid to be gratious that loves grace, and he a chriſtian that loves Chriſt as Chriſt deſerves, even with his whole heart; what company you now like you will have enough of hereafter, let it be good or bad. Pray God make you like Chriſt, then will you love him, and he will take you to himſelf; If that be not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe judge you.</p>
            <p>Reproves the moſt of the world and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> blames them for their ſelf-deceiving, that think they are very holy yet no way like unto Jeſus Chriſt. Blame I might open profane wretches; God knowes the world is full of ſuch that live in al riot and exceſſe and haſten to hell, ſo of Civil men that goe ſleepily and without making any noiſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: and alſo of men and women contenting themſelves with a forme of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38127:32"/> Godlineſs, how ſad is the condition of ſuch? how blame-worthy are they that regard not their ſouls? They take up ſo much of Religion as will get them ſome countenance from Gods people, but for God himſelfe they care not.<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.4.</note> I may ſay to ſuch as the Pſalmiſt to his fooles, deale not fooliſhly. For what will it advantage ſuch to carry ſome eſteeme for a ſhort time among men, and to their ſhame, nay confuſion (its feard) be diſcover'd at laſt? It is no comfort to a man in the end, that he was religious in ſhew only. And as their end will be comfortleſs that have onely the ſhell of goodneeſſ, ſo theirs that are open profane, and alſo that are careleſly ſecure. You'l blame a child for looſing a penny given to it, the very looſing is blam'd (the manner not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd) what may be ſaid to ſuch that looſe their ſouls? as they may be blam'd ſo pittied, but neither recovers them, they being once gone; out of hell is no redemption. Soules conſider this; have you not a place for duſt, &amp; another for Gold? I may ſay, ſo hath God. He hath a hel for filthy ſinners, &amp; a heaven for pure Saints. God is upon his worke of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38127:32"/> dayly, you will all find what I ſay true, he is ready to try you. Take heed in the day of ſifting you be not chaff, if you be, you will be burn'd in unquenchable fire. Like muſt to like, Chriſt and the Devil will have what belongs to them. Souls I deſire your change ſpeedily; for by nature you are all like Satan, you muſt be new caſt, have another forme, if like Chriſt. I cannot mend any of you by reproving (mending is Chriſts work) yet I ſhall as enabled pray, that they that are not chang'd into the Image of Chriſt may be, and where 'tis begun it may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> You it may be have a mind to aske me, why ſo few are like Chriſt, ſeeing 'tis ſuch an excellent ſtate, and alſo honourable &amp;c?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I may ſay becauſe they have not receiv'd of the heavenly gift, &amp; are not by heavens hand poliſhed. Beſides, 'tis not the faſhion of the world. To be holy is exceedingly out of faſhion in theſe times; to be holy is to be ſingular, the laſt is to be wondred at, if not diſdain'd; it ſets all men a wondering to behold the aſſemblies of Saints.<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.5.</note> Some-times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38127:33"/> wondring they are enrag'd againſt them;<note place="margin">Reges ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae inito inter ſe conſilio congregati ſunt contra hanc Dei civitatem, ejuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ad nos expugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerunt.</note> I ſhal ſpare any further diſcourſe upon ſuch that differ ſo much from Chriſt, I am ſure if they never be made like Chriſt, they will wiſh they had, if they be chang'd into the like Image I need not bid them, their own graces will quicken them to praiſe the Lord. The firſt Doctrine is left to your medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, I deſire you may be as like Chriſt as the Doctrine is like truth; the next thing to preſent to your ſoules is this. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> They that know Jeſus Chriſt may know Saints. I know many queſtions might be propounded about this Doctrin but I omit them, what may be ſaid of two men that are much a like, he that knows one may know the other, ſo he that knowes Chriſt may know Saints. I know no one ſurer way to try men by then this, looke well upon Chriſt, conſider his graces, and all his endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mor Dei eſt illud ſigillum, quo Deus electos &amp; credentes obſignat.</note> taſte his ſweetnes, ſmell his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour &amp; where you find that is like, what you find in Chriſt, conclude they are Saints. Men know their goods by the mark, their leaſes by the ſeale, ſervants by their livery, ſo may Saints be known by Chriſt. Study Chriſt well and thou
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38127:33"/> wilt ſay ſuch are Saints, let their appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances bee what they will, let them be by name <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> circumcis'd or not circumcis'd, if Saints their graces will diſcover what they be. Chriſtians judge not according to the fleſh and formes, but according to the Spirit, a gracious ſoul is lovely to a gracious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, let it be of never ſo different judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſome low things that are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to vaniſh.</p>
            <p>They are children of one Father, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> deſcended of one Royal ſtock. Know the Eldeſt child well, you may know the Younges, conſider of Chriſts comlines, &amp; the Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may the better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, know the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and you may know holy Saints, the voice of Chriſt, and the voice of Saints. God gifts and cloths his children much alike, what the eldeſt hath the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt hath the ſame, indeed the eldeſt is larges; and the difference is onely in the meaſure not in the manner; Al grace is in Chriſt, and ſome in Saints. There's grace in al, head and members have life, every part of the body its ornament, ſo whole Chriſt, and this in holines.</p>
            <p>Their employment is a like. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> Do you
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38127:34"/> know the buſines of Chriſt? can you ſay this is the work of Chriſt, and herein he is excercis'd? Conſider who acts like him, and then judge. Compare things together, the holy and heavenly work of Chriſt, let that be the pattern, eſteem and commend thoſe ſouls whoſe work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are moſt like the pattern. Children are commended that write moſt like the Copy, and ſo is the Limner whoſe draught is moſt like the body, whoſe picture agrees beſt with the life. Suffer a word of exhortation.<note place="margin">Eph. 5.1.</note> Be ye therefore followers of God, as deare childien, and walk in love, as Chriſt alſo hath loved us, and hath given himſelf for us, an offering, and a ſacrifice to God for a ſweet-ſmelling ſavour. Chriſt yeel'ds a ſweet ſavour in his love, and in his obedience:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.15.</note> ſo do Saints, they are unto God a ſweet ſavour. Study Chriſt ſoundly, and when you have done, ſee how men agree with Chriſt, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly let them have the repute of Saints. Be not partial in your judging, but judge righteous judgement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uſe.</note>You may now hint whence it is that Saints are no better known. I conceive it is becauſe Chriſt is not known. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:38127:34"/> of Chriſt effecteth an ignorance of Saints.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.8</note> Chriſt was kild by ſuch that knew him not, and ſo are Saints. How many precious Jewels have been taken for droſſe, and ſo caſt out? how many gracious ſouls eſteem'd not worthy to live? and why? becauſe like Chriſt,<note place="margin">Act. 22.22</note> both Chriſt and they taken for evil doers, for diſturbers of the places where they come, yea ſometime for blaſphemers: you ſeldom ſee any reverence godly ſouls that yield not reverence to the God of ſouls;<note place="margin">Joh. 16.2, 3.</note> that reſpect Saints that honour not Chriſt. Men that are fartheſt from Chriſt, are the lap-children of wicked men, if any have their reſpect they are ſuch that are like themſelves, ungodly. Good men, you complain of your ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, wrongs, and divers ſufferings in the world; and complain you may: your ſorrows are ungodly mens muſick; they never rejoyce more then when the Saints tears run down faſteſt. This hath and will be the worlds paſtime, even good-mens ſufferings. Chriſt ſufferings pleaſ'd the <hi>Jews</hi> heartily: ſo doth the ſufferings of Chriſts people, Jewiſh na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to this day. Men do they know not what, in wronging the deare jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38127:35"/> of God, and pluck on themſelves a moſt heavy wrath from the God of Saints. The works of wicked men now are ſuch as the wicked generations that went before,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.15.</note> for they killed the Lord Jeſus, and the prophets, and perſecuted Saints, and all was becauſe they were blinded of Satan, and the glorious Spirit of holines ſhone not into their ſouls to give them the knowledge of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. How were it poſſible that men ſhould be enemies to Chriſt or to Saints the friends of Chriſt, did they know what he hath ſuffered and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone for ſouls?<note place="margin">Amor <hi>è</hi> caelo ad terram eum traxit, ad colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affixit, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchro clauſit, ad inferos at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raxit.</note> how out of love and pitty he came down from heaven, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwent many a gracious ſuffering, and all to do poor wretched man good? but here is a ſad ſight, al is ſlighted of many. Is it not ſtrange to hear a groaning Chriſt, and ſinners mocking? a Chriſt wounded to the heart, and ſouls mad at heart againſt him? to ſee the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Father dying, and yet the children of that Father abus'd, and that by ſuch for whom the Father is ſuffering? It was an ungratful act of <hi>Joaſh</hi> to ſlay the child of <hi>Johoiada</hi> that had holp him to the Kingdome, but as the ſufferer prayed,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38127:35"/> God acted &amp; puniſhed the wicked doer. God is juſt, wait his time, and then ſee what he wil do to Chriſt and chriſtian wrongers. You have need of patience you Chriſt-like ſouls, you are ſufferers, you will be ſo in this world, you are not known neither is your Saviour, and indeed becauſe your glory is hid, is it that your ſufferings are open; but be of good chear, God will help you, he knows Chriſt, and he knows you, he holp Chriſt, and will help you. I ſhall ſay onely this to ſuch that ſay they know not who are Saints, what theſe Saints mean they know not, &amp;c. I fear you know not Chriſt, if it be ſo 'tis ſad with you, and your ſtate is miſerable, and were I able this day to weep, I ſhould willingly weep for ſuch that know not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Let not a form of worſhip bear o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermuch <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> ſway with you, and ſo think all Saints that are under ſuch a form, and for all others to thinke that they are heathen, to ſuppoſe that they are without Chriſt becauſe without ſuch a form, a form affected by you; Theſe forms of worſhip, I mean Idolizing them, hath made a miſerable ſtir a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mungſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38127:36"/> profeſſors. The devil hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken great advantage to nouriſh ſtrife and diſcord amongſt brethren by them, and he hath blaſted charity abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nay ſo much that ſome will not joyn in prayer with any unleſſe of their form, nor hear the word unleſſe from one of their judgment. Is this a knowing of Chriſt, &amp; then Saints; or is it a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing appearances, &amp; Saints by them? The Lord reconcile <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile.</hi> The foot may be lov'd though it be not an eye becauſe 'tis of the body, ſo may a ſoul though of a different outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance becauſe it belongs to Jeſus Chriſt. In the body there are ſeveral members, yet are all uſeful in their places, wherin the Lord hath been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to place them: ſo it is in the ſeveral attainments and Adminiſtrations the Saints are under. All may be uſeful, and he that is in the loweſt Attainment (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially that may be of ſome ſo judg'd) may there enjoy God, and be uſeful to the body, and though it ſee not with the eye, yet may it be a foot to help carry on the body. I could wiſh that we could more look after Chriſt, and where we find him eſteem them Saints, whether
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:38127:36"/> they be circumciſed or uncircumciſed, whether bond or free. I know not why any ſhould conſider them that are in a low appearance &amp; as 'tis judg'd in mean attainment. Who knows but Chriſt may be with them? if ſo, thats enough; if Chriſt aſcend they ſhall aſcend with him. <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke roſe as the waters did: ſo ſhall Saints as Chriſt pleaſeth to bear them up, and at length all forms ſhall die, and Chriſt to his appear all in all. For the reſurrection and appearance of the Lord is the death of man, and the death of forms, and the death of fleſh: for all theſe things are but ſhadows, and when Chriſt cleerly appears they ſhall be aboliſhed. The Lord make out his appearance clearly, that ſo we may know him, and by knowing him know thoſe that are his, and from a right knowing, love, and love increaſing, our mutual joy may abound in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Would you ſoules be taken for Saints?<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> do you deſire the people of God ſhould have ſuch an eſteem of you indeed? You muſt be like Chriſt, or they durſt not own you under that name, you muſt be anointed with that anonting he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38127:37"/> withal,<note place="margin">Ro. 8.9.</note> you muſt have the ſame ſpirit within and you muſt be faſhioned without like Chriſt,<note place="margin">Omnis vita noſtra con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formis illi reddatur, qui exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more noſtri totum ſae nobis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formavit.</note> your converſation muſt be holy and as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the Goſpel. Two cannot walk together except they agree ſaith God; now what agreement can be between Chriſt and <hi>Beliall?</hi> between the wolfe and the lamb? what agreement was there between Saints and <hi>Paul</hi> all that time he perſecuted? could Saints take him for a Saint then; No, he muſt be made a new creature, he muſt be changed, Chriſt muſt be revealed in him. Some of you are angry becauſe you are debar'd from ſomething that is the priviledge of Saints. Pray know this, Gods ſheepe are known by his mark, ſhew your mark, let appear that your ſpot is the ſpot of God, and ſuch as he puts on his flock. Every man may not ſit in Parliament, is ſuch that are choſen, and ſent, ſo not every one may fit in the aſſembly of the righteous, but ſuch that are called, and choſen, and faithful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> You will object it may be and ſay, what do I think you are not holy? do I not take you for Chriſtians? do I think th you have not a care to ſerve God
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38127:37"/> and live holily? do not wee (you'l ſay keep our church as much as any? do not we pray and hear? We were former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken for good people, and there was no exception, what muſt we, now be ſuſpected? muſt our faith be now call'd in queſtion? ſcuh things Carnall people object.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Soules from this plea I cannot ſay you are Saints. I know many a Nominall Chriſtian goes to hell, many go to Church (as they ſtile the houſe of publike worſhip) &amp; are never the more reformed,<note place="margin">Eccl. 8.10</note> they continue wicked and are unregenerated it may be for al this.<note place="margin">Ro. 2.28.</note> I may uſe <hi>Pauls</hi> words; He is not a <hi>Jew</hi> which is one outwordly, neither is that Circumciſition, which is outward in the fleſh;<note place="margin">
                  <p>Qui tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna &amp; nuncupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one eſt Judaeus, non coram Dei judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio conſetur Judaeus ſed is ſolus, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Non qui eſt in operto Chriſtianus is Chriſtianus eſt nec qui eſt in aperto tantum baptiſmus, is baptiſmus eſt &amp;c.</p>
               </note> Now know this that the meaning is I conceive, He is not a true <hi>Jew</hi> or true <hi>Iſraelite, viz.</hi> gracious, that can onely plead his naturall birth or the cutting off the foreskin of his fleſh, neither is he a true Chriſtian, that is ſo by name onely, and borne in a Chriſtian country, and that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the outward badge being ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with water. <hi>Paul</hi> diſcovered how little ſuch outward things profited,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38127:38"/> when he renounced all fleſhly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence;<note place="margin">Phil. 3.4</note> Though he could plead as great fleſhly priviledges as any, yet he counted all as nothing worth in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of Chriſt. When he had received Chriſt,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.13</note> he ſaw cleerly by that light, that manifeſts all things, that all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral endowments and enjoyments with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt were of no benefit to the ſoul. Now as <hi>Paul,</hi> though comparing them with Chriſt counted them dung and droſſe, yet he did not detract any thing from the endowments and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments themſelves.<note place="margin">Haec nihil detrahunt dignitati ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum, &amp;c.</note> No more would I from the name <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or from pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like meetings or, from baptiſm, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I am to give all their due; ſo that Chriſt be not rob'd but acknowledged all and in all. I muſt tell you ſouls, they are fooles and unwiſe that pride themſelves in any thing that is not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſt. Baptiſme is nothing, if a ſoul hath not Chriſt; a Sermon is nothing, preaching nothing, if Chriſt be not preached; the name Chriſtian no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if Chriſt be not in the ſoul. The ſum of the ſum of all is Chriſt. 'Tis a common fault (God weed it out of mens hearts) for men to vatut in ſome
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38127:38"/> outward thing, and glad many are if they can denominate themſelves of this or that opinion or judgement, or of this or that man as a hearer, follower or of his Congregation, or got into ſome attainement that bears high a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt profeſſours. I ſhall onely ſay this, beware you do not deceive your ſelves, Chriſt is all, and all you muſt have Chriſt, or you will periſh eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally. I might have added ſeverall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why Saints are ſo wary who they take into their fellowſhip, as that they will not take in ſuch that bear a name onely, and in life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are ſenſuall carnall, heatheniſh, deviliſh, nor ſuch as barely beleeve on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Chriſt without: that can ſpeake of the letter of ſcripture and the history of Chriſt but, have not a Chriſt manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed within, but I ſhal not ſtay here much; for Saints them already; and for others, they (as Swine pearles) will tread them under their foot; they will ſcorn them as that they ſavour of over much ſtrictneſſe and novelty; it may they will ſay of Independencie and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſme. But a word of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is uncomfortable to Saints to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:38127:39"/> take them into fellowſhip that have not a Chriſt within. Is it not uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable living for a living man to be yok'd to a dead body, and to have dead men for his Company What are men without Chriſt but dead men,<note place="margin">Eph. 2. 1. Joh. 1.22.</note> ſouls without life ſtincking, rotten loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſouls that have no comlineſſe?</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is dangerous to Saints to joyn in any intimate fellowſhip with ſuch, by reaſon they are infectious perſons; a body infected with the plague is not more apt to infect mens bodies, then ſinfull vile ſouls are ſuch that nouriſh fellowſhip with them.<note place="margin">pſ. 18.29.</note> Men are very apt to faſhion themſelves like thoſe with whom they converſe and live, to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate their words and actions, and to be confederate in their doings, and ſo allured or enticed from what is right and agreeable to the perfect rule of the word.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is ſcandalous, for if ſuch be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into fellowſhip and church ſociety that are vile or that have but a form of Godlineſſe, and ſo adorn not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Goſpell, how doth it give ungodly men occaſion to ſpeak evil, and to open their mouths againſt the way
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38127:39"/> of the <hi>Saints,</hi> and to ſtand out ſo much the more ſtifly by way of oppoſſition againſt truth, becauſe of ſome bad ones got into outward ſociety that have not the inward enjoyment of truth. Saints had need beware (upon this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) who they take into church-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, that ſo it be not ſuch that by falling off from holineſſe give offence, but ſuch that are held in by the power of truth to the credit of truth, and truths profeſſors with whom they are in communion.</p>
            <p>Souls you that know Chriſt look a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you; conſider of men rightly; take a ſerious conſideration of them;<note place="margin">Sanctam vitam cum ip ſo amant. Diſcite a me quia mitis ſum &amp; humilis corde. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis eſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doptivus Dei filius, vide quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſetur filius ille unigenitus.</note> &amp; take them for Saints that are like Chriſt, ſuch that are like holy as Chriſt is holy, pure as Chriſt is pure, precious as Chriſt is precious, ſweet &amp; lovely, comely beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> gentle &amp; lowly as <hi>Chriſt</hi> they that are Chriſts are like <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted ſonnes of God like the only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſonne of God, the younger brothers like the Elder, Saints like their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Chriſt is humble, gentle, loving, merciful, full of bowels of kindnes and goodnes, they that are Saints indeed are like him, he it is they ſtrive to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:38127:40"/> he they look vnto as their rule,<note place="margin">Sancta Chriſti vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, eſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecta vitae noſtrae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula.</note> he is the patterne they have always be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. I guide you not to this or that forme, attainment, opinion, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or the like, to find Saints; but I point out to you Chriſt, and if you ſee any like him eſteem them: if you find any that have the ſame ſpirit as Chriſt,<note place="margin">vbi ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus vnus, ibi eadem voluntas; ubi volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas eadem; ibi etiam actiones eaedem.</note> that have the ſame will, the ſame acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons look on them &amp; love them, and for Chriſts ſake eſteem them; becauſe they are like Chriſt the very image of Chriſt. The main reſolution of their ſouls, and actings of the body is to know God, and promote his glory, to aſcribe praiſes to him, to do good to Saints, to put forward whatſoever is agreeable to his wil with all their might.<note place="margin">Si propter Chriſtum proprio ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nori, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prio amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, propriae voluntati. in hac vita renunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura, ſui honoris, ſui amoris compotem te faciet.</note> 'Tis not mens frownes, tis not allurements, 'tis not loſſes, 'tis not Croſſes can deter them from the work of God: they know if they deny themſelves ſeeking here not their own honour nor ſelf advancings, but following the advice of Chriſt, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving his will, doing his work, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out themſelves wholly for him, he will reward them, by giving out unto them of his honour, of his love, and the like in the world to come. I ſhall
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:38127:40"/> leave you now to the ſearch and finding out of Saints, by the wiſdome of Chriſt owning and eſteeming ſuch for Saints that are like Jeſus Chriſt, they that know Chriſt may know Saints. And ſo much ſhall ſuffice to be ſpoken of that ſecond Doctrine. We ſhall as God ſhall enable us by his ſpirit give out ſomewhat more from the Text that may be of further uſe &amp; comfort to ſouls, which is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saints brought to heaven ſhall not have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother being,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>onely a perfecting of what is begun on earth.</hi> They have a glory already in them, upon them,<note place="margin">Joh. 17.22.23.</note> even the glory that was given to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in heaven they ſhall have more abundant glory. They have Somewhat for breeding, as heirs under age, not come to their full inheritance, yet growing to a ripeneſſe of years and ſo to a poſſeſſion of the inheritance, even a knowledge of the excellencies of God and Chriſt fully and clearly, yea and of their own excellency by vertue of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and communion with Father and ſonne; For then ſhall that glory be manifeſt and apparant above, which is not ſo manifeſt and apparent below. Chriſtians have ſome light now, though
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:38127:41"/> but ſmall, they have part of what they ſhall enjoy in perfection; they now ſee though but darkly, then face to face, clearly; They enjoy viſions of God though in a cloudy and darke manner. God and glory are reveal'd but in part to Saints whilſt here on earth, and all they ſee and know is but dark and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, to what they ſhall ſee and know: God communicates and makes out of his fulneſſe to thoſe are his here on earth, but the communication and making out of all fulneſſe it ſelf is only above in glory in the higheſt heavens, when they ſhal be brought to dwel with Chriſt to behold his glory, and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that marvellous Light, the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of which yet we are not able to behold. Chriſtians have had, and ſtill have, as much of God here, as ſuch veſſels could hold: here Saints are nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-hearted, and dim-ſighted, and cannot entertaine ſo much, nor ſee ſo clearly as they ſhall when they arrive at heaven, where their hearts ſhall be enlarg'd, and their ſight made fit, as to receive much, ſo to behold much of the excellencies of Glory.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:38127:41"/>
            <p>Souls, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> conſider what I am now about to ſpeak to you: have you a being now like the Saints in glory, yea like Chriſt in glory, is the life of glory begun here? is there any ſparks of that heavenly fire kindled in you? any drops of that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain? hath the light ſhin'd into you that ſhines in heaven? have you that joying you now hear on earth? that joyes Saints in bliſſe above? hath a ſight of God made you large to ſee more of him? can you ſay with the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 63.1, 2.</note> My ſoul thirſteth, and my fleſh longeth for thee, to ſee thy glory, ſo as I have ſeen it in the ſanctuary? hath glimpſe of beauty taken you? any thing of Chriſt delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Pray try what is in your inward man? do you find any light of love ſhining in? are you warm'd with any of this heavenly heate?<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.12.</note> I cannot preſſe this too much: doth God dwell in you? you are not like him if there be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwellings of God himſelf. I do not ſo much regard what you are without and in appearance. I would have you ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what within. There is great glory in heaven, there muſt be ſome glory in your ſouls here; yea and it muſt be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38127:42"/> ſuch glory as is in heaven, glory ſhines in Saints more clearly above, here it ſhines though but dimly, and they that ſhine here a little as ſparks ſhall ſhine exceeding brightly as the Sun in the kingdome of their Father,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.43.</note> here (if we are as we ſhould be and ſuch that ſhall increaſe in goodnes, &amp; have an addition to our joy) we have ſome inward taſte and feeling of the bleſſed comforts of God. Beloved that which I ſpeake to you of, concerns your ſouls, take heed they be not empty, take heed they be not void of all goodnes, deſtitute of the love and ſweet communion of God through Jeſus Chriſt. You know how it ſped with the five fooliſh Virgins that had no oyle in their lamps: let what befel them make you beware. 'Tis a wiſemans part to refrain from that way which others have periſhed in; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean <hi>birds</hi> may have gaudy outſides, the plain feather'd fowl may be wholſomeſt, beware that no man deceive you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 51.6. Pſa. 51.10.</hi> Innova in interiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus meis ſpiritum rectum.</note> and alſo be cautious that you wrong not your ſelves, know this that God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth truth in the inward parts; and a pure inſide; a clear heart was one thing <hi>David</hi> petition'd for, this you
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38127:42"/> ſhould ask, and this you muſt poſſeſſe if ever it be well with you. That ſoul is as it ſhould be when 'tis the ſeat, throne, and dwelling of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Are your ſouls rais'd ftom the dead? is there a power put forth in you, and that an exceeding great power, whereby you are delivered from ſin, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and ſelfe, and unable to walke as Spiritually alive according to the wil of God. Souls in glory are free ſouls, rais'd ſouls, ſouls ſet on high, ſouls exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſpiritualiz'd, wholly ſpiritual, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, ſouls in glorifying and praiſing God, 'tis their oontinual employment, they ceaſe not, they are alwayes buſied in what tends to Gods praiſe. Is there any likenes to this in you? are you fetcht out of darkneſſe? ſet at liberty? made able for the work of God? Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are firſt Apprentices, Apprentices are in the way to freedom, what are Saints in heaven but freemen? ſuch that have ſerv'd out their time on earth: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider chriſtians are you bound to God? doth he teach you? doe you now ſerve him? are you wholly his? do you not ſerve Satan, world, nor ſelfe, but God? it will be but a few yeares but you
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:38127:43"/> ſhall be advanced higher, advanc'd into ſublime and tranſcendent glory, to ſit with Saints, and there with your fellow-brethren to ſing Hallelujahs for evermore.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is there a prizing of the things of glory? They that are like Chriſt, eſteem, love, prize, the things of Chriſt, and what Chriſt doth eſteeme, love, prize; they eſteeme creature things in their places as they ought; yet all theſe are but dung and droſſe in compariſon of the excellencies of grace and glory. Soul-neceſſities are not ſatisfied with creature-things: they free not from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, they reveale not the love of God, nor eaſe the ſoul of its trouble; if troubl'd for want of the loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Lord. Saints in glory are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from all miſery and enjoy ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of conſolation, they that are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glory-ward ſhall be eas'd, ſhall have their ful of joy: they eye the pleaſures and bliſſe of heaven, they have thoughts upon them, they are much taken up with them in their meditations. Saints in heaven are pleas'd with the viſible glory they injoy. Saints on earth are pleas'd, in that through faith they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:38127:43"/> there is a reward laid up for them, that they ſhall poſſeſſe an inheritance incorruptible, and undefiled,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.4.</note> and that fadeth not away, reſerved in heaven for them. Souls you know what you prize, what is delightful to you, you can tell whether earthly, or heavenly, carnal or ſpiritual things: ſurely if drawing towards heaven, they are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things delight you; they that are in glory rejoyce in their glorious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, they that are in grace going to glory, rejoyce through faith in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving what is laid up for them, and what they ſhall enjoy: they exſpect the accompliſhing of promiſes; and their accompliſhing, tends to gracious ſouls advancing, and crowning in glory with an everlaſting diadem. Conſider of this I pray, take much care in trying whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be in the right way to perfect peace: you would not willingly be cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned in any earthly things, beware you be not cheated in this that concernes your ſoules, and ſo loſe your ſoules: if you ſhould, I need not ſay you are undone, you will to your ſorrow finde it; but I hope you will be careful in this. I can but adviſe, 'tis God muſt make
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:38127:44"/> you wiſe; I can but inſtruct, 'tis the Lord muſt make you to receive inſtruction. Try all things, try earthly things, you will ſee them vanity, try Spiritual things, God grant you knowledge to diſerne, and wiſdome to prize and hold faſt what is good.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Is to ſpeake comfort to ſouls. What Revelations, have you now; you ſhall have more; what diſcoveries of love now you ſhall have more large manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons heareafter; God ſpeaks good to ſouls now, and gives in ſomewhat of love, but 'tis here a little and there a little, now and then a drop to keep their hearts open; but in heaven God comunicates all at once: here he gives out what he gives in degrees, &amp; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Saints capacity to receive; but in heaven the whole ſhall be poſſes'd, that God hath in ſtore for them that love him; they ſhall have perfect holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, compleat happines, and pure ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituality.<note place="margin">Animorum ſumma pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas, ſtupenda corporum charita, &amp;c.</note> There natures ſhall be ſpotleſs, and there actions blameleſſe, an orient ſplendour and matchleſſe brightneſs of reſplendent light ſhall cover the whole man as a garment. Oh what an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, unconceiveable, and unparallel'd
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38127:44"/> gladnes throughout the ſoul, ſpirit, &amp; whloe man wil this occaſion? Saints here deſire much, and have ſomewhat of heavens excellency but their deſires are not fully ſatisfied,<note place="margin">Quicquid deſiderare poterunt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecti, illic invenient: quia coram a facie ad faciem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuentur eum qui eſt omnia.</note> and in heaven they ſhal have their ful, inſomuch that deſires ſhal ceaſe, not longing after more, for God ſhal communicate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe fully and at once to Saints there. Saints have now ſome beauty, ſome comlines, they are in part ſanctified, but in heaven they ſhal be fully ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, all glorious, this corruptible muſt put on incorruption, and this mortal muſt put on immortality, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of evil ſhall not be in ſouls, there ſhal be no unſoundnes of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor taints of error, no impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie nor imbecillity of affections in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Saints love to Chriſt, ſhal not be cold, weak and feeble, but it ſhall be hot, ſtrong, perfect, they ſhal be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any imperfection. Nothing in them, or what is done by them ſhal be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy,<note place="margin">Similes erimus ipſi Deo benedicto in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</note> they ſhal be like the bleſſed God for ever. Is not this a word of comfort now? wil it not be much more a precious ſoul-rejoycing to enjoy this purity, this ſamctity, this holineſſe, of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:38127:45"/> being made a excellent beautiful like An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,<note place="margin">Angelis &amp; ſibi ipſi nos ſimiles reddit.</note> yea like God himſelf? There ſhal be nothing amiſſe in the ſoul; it ſhal be all glorious: no blindneſſe, lameneſſe, deafneſſe, nor crookedneſſe, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity ſhal be on the body: the bodies of Saints in glory that be handſome, faire, comely, beautiful; yea like unto the glorious body of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> yea, and which is more, they ſhal in the whole body be like unto his glorious body.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eadem corpora, quae hic cum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixa ſunt, una cum Chriſto in caeleſti be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitudine glorifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note>Theſe very bodies of Saints that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer now with and for Chriſt, ſhal with Chriſt in heavenly bliſſe be glorified with him; yea they ſhal have ſuch glory as he hath. This Souls I ſhal leave to you to admire. I cannot ſufficiently and to the ful in words diſcover it to you; 'Tis a wonder to thinke that they that are gracious and ſo like Chriſt here, ſhould be in heaven as handſome bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Chriſt is,<note place="margin">—Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria nulla lingua ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari poteſt.</note> and have as comely a perſon and feature as he himſelf has, whom the Father loves dearly, that their bodies ſhal be in all places like to Chriſts body. Beloved, may not this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us in trouble, to venture life and limb for God, rather then that God ſhould loſe his glory; ſeeing that he
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38127:45"/> can make up all again, and ſupply all wants, and wil make every one perfect at laſt: and alſo not to be troubled as concerning Death, with any diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable thoughts of worms eating and deſtroying the fleſh, with rottenneſſe ſeiſing upon the body, and the like; knowing that Chriſt at laſt wil reſtore all perfect.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Saints, you have now ſome wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge, you ſhal have more abundant, you ſhal have more wiſdome,<note place="margin">Iſa Dei ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſam eis oſtendet, &amp;c.</note> you ſhal have clearer know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the things of God and Chriſt, and of heaven; ſurely knowledge is an exellent thing, eſpecially Divine and Heavenly knowledge, knowledge in the myſtery of ſalvation. What is it that ſome would not give for knowledge now in Arts and Tongues, and in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-truths, yea to know God rightly? In heaven Saints you ſhall have an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite and perfect knowledge of God; ye ſhal ſee him not only mentally and contemplatively, but alſo with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies eyes corporally; ſo <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 19.25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter day upon the earth. And though after my skin, worms deſtroy this body, yet
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38127:46"/> in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God: Whome I ſhall ſee for my ſelf, and mine eyes ſhall behold, and not another;</hi> This Chriſtians I conceive may make your longings to be eager after heaven, and exceedingly rejoyce to thinke you ſhal ſee God, to ſee God as he is in himſelf, and as he Is in you; And all this in a ſpiritual manner, for all knowledge in heaven ſhal be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual. I might enlarge my ſelf more on this, but I forbear according to what of God is given in to you, ſuch is your knowledge already, and as God ſhal be reveal'd, knowledge ſhal encreaſe, and at laſt you ſhal in glory know as you are known.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Saints ſhal in heaven have a ful fruition of Chriſt, a ful ſight of their ſweet Saviour,<note place="margin">Chridum videre, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabit omnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaudia. Superabit omnia cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis noſtoi deſideria.</note> ſuch a ſight that ſhal give in unſpeakable joy, ſuch enjoyment that ſhal bring more joy then heart can wiſh; no tongue can expreſs, no heart can conceive what conſolation they have that ſhal enjoy Chriſt and dwel with him for ever. To ſee Chriſt to dwel and be with Chriſt, brings to ſoules wounderful happines. This makes ſouls cry out how long Lord Jeſus is it ere thou wilt bring us to glory, where
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38127:46"/> we may have beauty preſented to our ſight, ſweetnes to our taſte amongſt men,<note place="margin">Pulchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo erit viſui, mel guſtui, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thara audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui, balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num olfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctui, flos actui.</note> muſick to our eare, what is odoriferous to our ſmelling, and delightful to be touch'd and handled, the ſoul alſo fil'd with light, and comfort, every faculty having what is pleaſant to it given out freely and fully; O bleſſed condition! O ſweet life! O happy being! to be brought into the Court of the glorious God, to the ſociety of Saints,<note place="margin">Jeſu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, ſponſe animaemeae ſuaviſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</note> into the boſome of ſweet and bleſſed Jeſus, the loving, and ever-glorious husband to bleſſed ſouls! Love is abundantly ſhown on earth by Chriſt to thoſe that are Chriſts, in their affaires to direct them, in their troubles to help them, in their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to deliver them; in beſtowing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and excellent benefits both of grace and nature, and of creature-things: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in diſappointing the dangerous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of enemies, in fruſtrating the ſubtile and crafty plottings of Satan, in beating downe the power of corruption and the like: here is much of mercy and goodnes in all this, but the crown and perfection of all, is the bringing, ſeating, crowning of ſouls in glory. How beautiful are ſouls in that day! how
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38127:47"/> glorious! how lifted up! how exalted! how honour'd when they ſhal not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſee Chriſt, but they ſhal live with him! Not alone, behold him in a Throne at the right-hand of the maieſty on high, but they ſhal be ſeated in Thrones with him! Rejoyce O ſouls in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of this, let the conſideration hereof be ſweet and pleaſant to you, for you ſhal be ever with Chriſt the Lord;<note place="margin">Ibi ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, ſecura tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilla ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunditas, jucunda felicitas, felix ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitas, aeterna beatitas. Gaudium erit ſine triſtitia, quod con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam laeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, ſalus erit ſine dolore, vita ſine labore lux ſine tenebris, amor nunquam tepeſcet; gaudium nunquam decreſcet; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitus non audietur, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dolor ſentietur, triſte nihil videbitur, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a ſemper habebitur, &amp;c.</note> with Chriſt the glorious; there ſhal you be ſafe, there ſhal you have delight, there ſhal you have happines and that eternal happines and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bleſſednes, all good, all the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent enjoyments of heaven ſhal be end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, light endleſſe, joy endleſſe, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure endleſſe, friendſhip endleſſe: and as endleſſe, ſo pure without mixture; there ſhal in Chriſts Armes, in Chriſts pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents be joy without ſorrow, health without grief, life without labour, light without darkneſſe, continual freſh and flouriſhing love, abounding joy, mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhal not be there, neither ſhal there
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38127:47"/> be any grief, ſorrow or ſadnes or any ſuch thing. I deſire to ſpeak more clearely of theſe things but I cannot utter them as they deſerve, you that have had any refreſhing from Chriſt here, can beſt judge and diſcerne what it is to poſſeſſe him wholly, and live with him altogether.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſtians, in glory you ſhal have much happines ariſe to you from the ſweet communion and bleſſed fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip you ſhal have with Saints, you know ſome Saints now and you take ſome delight in their company, you are glad when you can meet with them to converſe and talke with them, and to joyne in ordinances, your joy in theſe things ſhal be much more abundant, for you ſhal know all the bleſſed Saints in glory: they that were taken up thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before you, and they that ſhal come thither after you, ſhal be known of you, and you known of them. All Saints ſhal be known of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Saint, and every particular Saint ſhal be known of all, <hi>in coelo nullus erit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienus,</hi> there ſhal be no ſtranger in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, a Saint there ſhal have as much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance as all the Saints in glory
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38127:48"/> may afford, &amp; as many friends as there are Saints. You that now deſire com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with holy ſouls, ſhal have your fill of familarity; you that joy to ſee and meet with Saints now, ſhal have your joy increas'd. Chriſtians on earth complain of the ſtrangnes of other Chriſtians, but in heaven there ſhal be no cauſe of ſuch complaints: as we ſhal be joyned one to another, and all to the Lord,<note place="margin">Nemo ibi laediiur, iraſcitur nemo, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, cupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditas nulla exardeſcit &amp;c.</note> ſo ſhal we love one another in the Lord. In glory none ſhal hurt other, none ſhal envy other, none ſhal deſire others good: for every one ſhal have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, even his fil of good; and ſhal rejoyce to ſee one another happy: conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der I pray what love to Saints now; what delight in their company; what refreſhment to ſee the faces of Saints; and enjoy the fellowſhip of ſanctified ſoules, if it be right, if truely ſpiritual, and what it ſhould be. It wil heareafter ſatisfie you to the ful when you ſhal have the perfect knowledge of al Saints. Let this comfort you againſt worldly mens ſlightings, yea and good mens ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; as for worldlings ſlightings care not, they are ſuch that ſhal be ſhut out from the preſence of God and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38127:48"/> of Saints. And for any Saints ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be not grieved, it wil not long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue: in heaven there is no ſuch thing there all Saints ſhal be kind each to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhal know each other perfectly, and love each other ſincerely and truly. Happy are they that have ſome begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of ſanctified love and communion with the holy and beloved ones of Jeſus Chriſt now; it ſhal encreaſe and be more abundant, as they growe up in Jeſus. Rejoyce in this Chriſtians, you ſhal ſee, know, have fellowſhip, dwel with for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, all bleſſed Saints, ſuch as, <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 8.11</note> 
               <hi>Jſaac, Jacob, Noah, David, Daniel, Paul, Sarah, Rebeccah,</hi> the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> &amp;c. you ſhal know their perſons, names, natures, Excellencies, delight in them, and they in you. I ſhal ſpeak no more of this Uſe. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Si in hac vita non guſtes ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternae feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatis ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, nunquam plenum percipies comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum.</note> let me give out ſomewhat by way of reproofe to ſuch men, that thinke they ſhal goe to heaven, and hope they ſhal dwel in glory hereafter, yet deſpiſe nothing more then what is heavenly, and what tends to help them thither; let ſuch be aſſured that they that have not ſome taſte and relliſh of heavenly things now, and delight in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38127:49"/> them wil never have their ful ſotiety in glory. Doe you thinke to goe to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that now hate holines, and ſpeak evil of the wayes of the Lord? That ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre Saints, as bad as the ſight of Toads, what wil you doe in heaven? you cannot abide praiſes &amp; hallelujahs and the glorious exerciſes of Saints, you cannot endure the fellowſhip of holy men and women, you abhor them now, yet they are not ſo pure as they ſhal be; and then doubtleſs you wil loath them more. Do not ſome of you abhorre being in places and amongſt people where Godlines is in exerciſe? do you not delight to be where you may drink and ſwel, ſing and roare, card and dice, hunt and hawk, mock and jeere, ſcoffe and deride goodnes and good-men? nay if it were in your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, would you not kil &amp; ſlay the Saints? do you not defie their waies, courſes, and behaviour, yea and that becauſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, pure, ſincere, upright and ſuch as are becoming the Goſpel of the bleſſed God? Conſider, I pray, your ſelves whether you are not ſuch that God himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves,<note place="margin">Pſ. 50.17.</note> for hating inſtruction and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his holy and heavenly councel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38127:49"/> your backs, and for letting your mouth be open to ſpeak evil, yea and that againſt the righteous? Do you thinke that God wil ſet ſuch with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in glory hereafter, that now caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide his councel, that wil not be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by him? honour ſuch with his Saints that now deſpiſe them? place ſuch in the kingdome of glory that now ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor the heirs of glory? No, no, he hath a place for ſuch naughty wretches to put them by themſelves,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 9.17</hi> Aeternis addicti ſuppliciis.</note> they ſhal be turned into hel; there the being of wicked men ſhal be; Thinke of this you Saint-haters, you Sermon-deſpiſers, you wicked mockers and ſcoffers at goodneſſe, you that are the wretches propheſied of, that ſhould be brought forth and come into the world in the latter daies, that ſhould appear unholy, and that ſhould be haters of ſuch as are good;<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.1, 2, 3.</note> What is it that ſome of you would do to the conſcionable imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of holineſs, were they in your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? would you not impriſon them, famiſh them, ſlay them, ſhew much cruelty to them? and would you not pluck down the pure preaching of Jeſus Chriſt, and obſtruct the perfect and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38127:50"/> walking of Saints? are not your hearts now againſt ſuch men, and ſuch doings? and do you not wiſh your hands at liberty to act ſome enterpriſes againſt what is holy &amp; good? againſt that which you cal Sects and Factions, and againſt ſuch as you ſay bring all out of order, that turn the world upſide down? I know not your thoughts within, you are privy to what dwels in your own breaſt. <hi>Paul</hi> was once as violent againſt goodneſſe and goodmen as any of you, and doubtleſſe had he been then asked, what <hi>Saul</hi> doſt thou think wil become of thy ſoul? doſt thou think thou ſhalt go to heaven? that thou ſhalt dwell with the ever-living God? with holy Angels and bleſſed Saints? he would have ſaid he hoped he ſhould go to heaven as ſoon any man living; but had the Lord let him go on in his way, &amp; not ſhewed him mercy, what had he come of his ſoul? Let this be diſgeſted in your ſouls: and know that glory and eternal happineſs is provided for ſuch that are waſhed, for ſuch that are ſanctified, for ſuch that are juſtified in the name of the Lord Jeſus, &amp; by the ſpirit of our God: and ſuch muſt you be, if ever brought to heaven. You
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38127:50"/> are by nature vile, filthy and naked;<note place="margin">Nuda erat ſponſa, nec poterat ad regale cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtis regni palatium ita nuda introduci; Ipſe induit eam veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis &amp; juſtitiae. Juimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum erat ſponſae ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus caele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti patri ſed ipſe il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud per a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerbiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliavit. <hi>Cant. 5.21</hi> Erit ibi praeſentia omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li &amp; erit a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tia om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>boni.</note> you muſt be clothed as Saints, with the robes of righteouſneſſe and garments of ſalvation if brought into the Palace of glory, the dweling of the great God where he ſits on his Throne and all his bleſſed Saints about him. I have this comfort yet of ſuch that are enemies to God and what is good, That it is in the power of the Lord for to change them, he can inſtruct them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and call them to holineſſe, and reconcile them to himſelf: but ſhould not the Lord thus work upon you that are revilers, ſlanderers, perſecutors, and the like, you ſhall not inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, but you would be caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into utter darkneſſe into unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able torments, to be tormented with the Devil and his Angels, into ſuch a place of ſuffering, where you ſhould have no mercy, no good, no comfort, no eaſe, no friend, no pitty: Miſerable, miſerable, beyond expreſſion, miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhall they be in torments for ever, that now torment the holy ones of the Lord, and the bleſſed members of Chriſt by their evill ſpeakings and evill doings: ſuch ſhall be puniſhed with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:38127:51"/> deſtruction,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.9</note> and be deprived of all mercy and comfort; I ſpeak not theſe things to trouble you, but in pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to admoniſh you, and my prayer ſhall be tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lion may lie down with the Lambe, that from Comings in of truth into your ſoules, you may be overcome of truth, and ſo ſubmit to it, that you may ſweetly accord and friendly agree with the children of truth, and all that in truth profeſſe truth; That you may ſpeak and act the ſame things, and that there may be no diviſions amongſt you: as you hope to dwell with the Prince of peace, and with the Saints of peace, now live peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably; follow after peace, and what may make for quietneſſe in the waies of God. Seeing you are apt to ſay, you have hopes to be ſaved; do like them that ſhal be ſaved: harme not, but help ſuch that are beloved of him that muſt ſave you if ever ſaved; Conſider of what hath been ſaid &amp; the Lord give you aright un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of al things, that may make you holy, gentle, courteous, peaceable, in life; and alſo honourable, bleſſed, happy and glorious for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> The life of Saints upon earth is a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:38127:51"/> rare life, an excellent, holy, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly being, a being that tends to the glory, honour and praiſe of God, to the exalting of his great mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and declaring his name and power: 'tis a life wherein men that are holy, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to improve themſelves with <hi>all</hi> that is theirs in a way of duty to be ſerviceable to the God of holines; As they have beginnings of the life of glory in the kingdome of grace, ſo according to what is begun and the gift given do they act, here in grace ſutable to what is done in glory. They are not perfect here, they have their failings, yet by the comings in of God they ſtrive to be like God, and according to the gifts of the Spirit, are they ſpiritual exercis'd; they are ſpiritual in their prayers; ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual in their preaching; ſpiritual in their hearing, ſpiritual in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; ſtriving to walke after the Spirit, endeavouring to give up their <hi>all,</hi> to Chriſt that is <hi>all</hi> and in <hi>all. All</hi> their wiſedome, <hi>all</hi> their might, <hi>all</hi> their ſtrength, <hi>all</hi> their endowments, <hi>all</hi> their places, <hi>all</hi> of ſoule, <hi>all</hi> of body, <hi>all</hi> of liberty, riches, honour, in a word, <hi>all.</hi> Chriſt hath done ſo much for them
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:38127:52"/> that they thinke, they can never do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for him, they think, they can never praiſe him enough, nor extol him as they ought, nor give the honour that is due to him. They are alwaies complaining of deadnes, and darknes, and weaknes, and inability to behold, to admire, to commend, to advance the ſweetnes, goodnes, mercy and comforts that Chriſt gives out to them: they are longing for more abilities to ſerve the Lord Jeſus. Faine would they do, as they in glory do, and they wait daily, earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſtly exſpecting to be brought to glory that they may enjoy that in fulnes which here they have in part, and that fulnes being injoy'd, employ it to the honour and praiſe of the giver. Soules, they are not common men that live the life of Saints, neither is their life a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon life. Saints are jewels, jewels are excellent things: there is that in a jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el that is not in ordinary and common ſtones: jewels have an excellency in them, ſo have Saints; and this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency is uſeful, to Chriſt, and what Chriſt adviſeth. The Excellency in Saints is given into them from Chriſt, and as is comes from Chriſt, it is altogether for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:38127:52"/> returning to Chriſt. Chriſt in giving out his Excellency to Saints, doth open his heaet to Saints and doth alſo open Saints hearts. The one is opened for goodnes to goe forth, the other for goodnes to come in; and goodnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing receiv'd in, wil not lie ſtil: it wil ſet ſuch that have it upon employments ſutable to the wil of Chriſt, as by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what is Chriſts: 'tis in ſome meaſure changd into the likenes of Chriſt: by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Chriſts love, the hearts of ſuch receivers are chang'd into the nature of Chriſts heart, and ſo become heavenly, heavenly within, and being heavenly within, it wil be heavenly without: The fruit like the ſeed, Saints like Chriſt. Excellent things are ſpoken of Saints in glory, ſo of Saints on earth. The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of Saints in glory is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable. They enjoy perfection, and from that perfection act; The amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe and admirablenes of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, drawes out all the abilities of Saints when in heaven to act anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto the Lawes nearenes, and dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſuch a relation as is betweene God and them. So here on earth ſuch that enjoy God though they cannot do
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38127:53"/> for God ſo immediately and fully, yet it is their deſire to cloſe with God, and to give out themſelves to God; and to carry themſelves in-offenſively in the world, and as much as in them lies to do good to all; Excellent things are ſpoken of the City of God, of the holy <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of the Lambes wife, of ſhee that is a dreſſing, a making ready for to be joyn'd to Chriſt. Shee is beautiful now, but ſhe ſhal appear more beautiful, ſhee is faire and pleaſant, and now the delight of Chriſt, his love, his dove, his undefiled; ſhee ſhal be the ſame in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, onely this more perfect. Chriſts ſpouſe, his Siſter, his dove, is but one, ſhee that is his on earth, ſhal be his in glory, ſhee that is his faire one here, ſhal be his glorious one above, that now is his boſome friend, ſhal be his Throne-companion.<note place="margin">Throni ſui compos.</note> The deſires (I know) of all you that are Godly, that are ſome of Chriſts holy ones, (ſpeake experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) is, that your ſweet Saviour would now raiſe all your deſires to him, faſten all your thoughts upon him, draw all the powers of your ſouls up on high to him, free you from every weight that holdeth you down, knit you to him
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:38127:53"/> with a knot of love, that ſo your joy in the injoyment of him might be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, your fellowſhip with Saints ſweet, your dayly walking heavenly, giving occaſions to all that are Godly to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie God on your behalf; Look to it Souls, you are in ſome meaſure glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous now, if you are ſuch that ſhal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with Chriſt in glory hereafter: That glory is ſparkl'd in now, which ſhal ſhine in clearly and apparently: you have now ſome beams, ſhortly the ful light of the clear and glorious Sun him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. For the ever-bleſſed and glorious God wil let in ſuch a light, ſuch a clear light, ſuch a great light, and withal give ſuch a great ſtrength of light unto Saints, that they ſhal be wholly light, and in them shal be no darkneſs at all. Beloved, I now commend you to God, that can make you children of Light, and enable you as children of Light to walk in Light, to the praiſe of his great name, and to the refreshing of the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of Gods people, to the rejoycing of all that delight in goodneſſe. Chriſts Saints are all rare pieces, God grant all theſe pieces may be ſet in order, fitly u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited together, then wil glory appear,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38127:54"/> exceeding glory, tranſcendent glory, glory in the Church, glory on earth like that glory that is amongſt the Saints that are Triumphant in heaven. I shal ſay no more of that Doctrine: I shal yet give out ſomewhat from the Text that may be further uſeful to your ſouls, and it is this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> There are ſome precious ſouls in the world, in this ſinful world, in this wicked, vile, ignorant and naughty world,<note place="margin">Joh. 17.24 1 Joh. 5.19. Joh. 12.31. &amp; 14.20.16.11. 2 Cor. 4.4. Iſa. 5.14. Mat 7.13. Jer. 3.14. Rom. 11.5 Luke 12.32. Rev. 3.4. Col. 2.22. 1 Joh. 5.5. Joh. 1.13.</note> in this world wherein Satan bears ſuch ſway, who is the Prince of the world, a cheif one in it ſo farre as it is a ſinful world and inhabited with ſinful men. The Devil hath many, nay the greateſt part; yet God hath ſome, a remnant, here and there one, a little flock, a few that are undefiled and that are lovely before him, that have kept their garments cleane, that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable, &amp; unreprovable before him, they have overcome the world, being borne, not of bloud, nor of the wil of the fleſh, nor of the wil of man, but of God. Every age (though it hath brought forth never ſo many weeds, though it hath abounded in traſh yet) hath brough forth ſome precious flowers,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:38127:54"/> ſome jewels have been found amongſt the rubbiſh. In the firſt degenerate age, there was an <hi>Abel,</hi> after that a <hi>Seth</hi> and to him was borne <hi>Enos;</hi> at which time men began to cal upon the name of the Lord.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.26</note> After that <hi>Enoch</hi> that walked with God, one that was the Phenix of that age,<note place="margin">Gen. 5.24</note> one that was tranſlated out of his own being, into a being in God, one that loſt nothing, by loſing what was his own by noture and according to the fleſh. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this God left not himſelf without teſtimony; Though the wickedneſſe of man was great in the earth and the whole earth was corrupt before God,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.9.</note> yet then appeared <hi>Noah</hi> a juſt man and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in his generations,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.9.</note> and one that walked with God, on that gave up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to God, to be at his direction and at his ſervice to do what was agreeable to the wil of the Lord. And as the world was repleniſhed, and grew on, though there were many wicked men and much wickedneſſe in the world, yet ſome God had that were good, though very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and hardly to be perceiv'd in thoſe darke times. At length appear'd <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> after him <hi>Jſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worthies, and when <hi>Elijah</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:38127:55"/> of the worlds emptines in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of good men, and that he alone was left, yet God tels him he had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thouſand in <hi>Iſrael</hi> that had not bowed the knee to <hi>Baall.</hi> I confeſſe 'its a very few conſidering how many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands were in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet you ſee there were ſome though hid and conceal'd in thoſe cloudy daies of Idolatry and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.<note place="margin">1 King. 19.18.</note> God may let men follow their owne pernicious waies, and there may be a great forſaking of goodnes, yet ſome ſhal cleave to truth, though it may be but a few,<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.13.</note> a tenth. There may be many weeds in a garden, yet ſome good herb may be found; abundance of trees in a feild, yet ſome corne; a world of earth, yet ſome vains of precious oare; a great deale of clay, of durt and ſtones, yet ſome pearles and precious jewels are now and then found. God hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent material, here and there, he wil bring them together, and of them make a famous ſtructure; build his Church,<note place="margin">Iſa. 54.12, 13.</note> whoſe foundations ſhal be laid with ſaphires, whoſe windowes ſhal be made of agates, and gates of carbuncles &amp; al her borders of pleaſant ſtones. This points out the excellency of Saints, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:38127:55"/> alſo what a comly thing it is to ſee them joyn'd together in a right order, by the wiſdome of God. God hath a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly City to build, which is admirably deſcrib'd <hi>Revelations,</hi> 21. My brethren I need not tel you how Satan the world fleſh, and many enemies, have labour'd to root out in all ages thoſe that clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and readily appear'd for God, yet God hath preſerv'd ſome to ſhine as lights, and to hold out his name, and enemies could never ſo prevaile as to raze out all the Saints nor to take away truth wholly; but ſtil the Lord continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome precious ones, ſome holy and excellent ſoules to ſhine out as lights in a darke place; a ſeed was left, though covered with clods, that the Lord hath nouriſhed, and which through his bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings hath ſprung up, and brought forth fruit, ſo that ſome peecious ſouls have ſtil appear'd. We have ſeen bad times, and bad times are, and 'tis likly wil be, yet all you that have any knowledge in rhe things of Chriſt, cannot but ſay ſome holy ſouls there were, in thoſe bad times; ſome there are in theſe evil daies; and ſome precious ones ſhal be as long as the Sun and Moon endureth
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:38127:56"/> as long as there are any people in the world there ſhal be ſome good: you that live now meet with ſome precious ſouls up and downe, here and there: you or they that ſhal live hereafter wil finde that God hath a ſprinkling ſome, a few: I ſhal ſpeak to what is preſent, to what is in hand, there are ſome precious ſouls in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> There are ſome in the world that are like Chriſt, they have ſuch a life, ſuch gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſuch excellency, there life is Chriſt within, 'its Chriſt living in them, their wiſedome is Chriſt, their righteouſnes Chriſt, their juſtification, ſanctification is Chriſt; Chriſt to ſuch is all. Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are tranſlated into Chriſt, they are one with Chriſt, they are nothing in themſelves, ſelfe is paſt away, they have a new ſelfe, Chriſt is their ſelfe, they have an intire being in Chriſt, yea God himſelfe is within ſuch, and from union with God is there likenes to God, and their preciouſnes is from enjoying God. God makes that precious that is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; precious ſouls are Gods work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip. Look upon Saints after the fleſh, and in outward appearances, you cannot it may be ſay they are ſo preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:38127:56"/> but conſider them as in Chriſt and Chriſt in them. Look upon Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in them; and boubtles Chriſt wil in them be precious;<note place="margin">Magna quidem in Eccleſia Dei excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia: ſect ea non ſunt omnibus obvia.</note> many ſee not this excellency in Saints becauſe 'tis hidden. Chriſt in them is hidden from many; but where Chriſt appeares, the ſouls of ſuch according to what of Chriſt is ſeen, appear precious.</p>
            <p>There are ſome that are lov'd as <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Chriſt, lov'd with the ſame love, the ſame pure, free, intire love that Chriſt hath, given out from the Father, they have given out to them, running into them, ſhining upon them, theſe are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. Love is that which doth beautifie ſoules, ſouls are faire as lov'd, excellent as lov'd, glorious as lov'd. There is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding bravery and beauty in a ſoule that hath much of love; what made Chriſt ſo priz'd ſo highly eſteem'd, the chiefeſt of Ten thouſand; but the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of heavenly love that was in him: the more there is of heavenly love the more excellent. 'Tis not Noblenes of birth, beauty of face, greatnes of parts, much learning that makes men precious, but 'tis being borne of God, endued with grace, partaking of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:38127:57"/> things and what is heavenly that makes one precious.<note place="margin">Tantus quiſque eſt quantus eſt apud Deum.</note> As one ſaith of the worth of a man, he is ſo much worth, as he is worth in Gods account; ſo I may ſay he is ſo far precious as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking in love, as enjoying that which the world doth not. A precious ſtone is a ſtone that hath a vertue &amp; excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which the common ordinary ſtones have not: ſo tis with precious, rare, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſoules, they have ſomewhat the men of the world have not, &amp; that is love,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.17</note> the ſame love that is given out to Chriſt. The worth of this love none knowes but they that enjoy it.</p>
            <p>There are ſome in whom the Lord dwels, ſome in this word that are his temple, palace, throne: theſe are excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ones. Gods dwelling place, the dwelling of his glory is a precious place: they are precious ſoules, ſoules bravely adorned, ſoules excellently trim'd that are the court of the great God. Princes houſes are richly furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: ſo are the ſoules of Saints, Gods houſes. There are ſome that put out all their might, ſtrength, power, abilities, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages for Chriſts cauſe, for what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes him, and what is his. Theſe are
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:38127:57"/> precious ſouls, <hi>Paul</hi> was a predious ſoul &amp; it appear'd in his appearing ſo much for Chriſt, that he was not deter'd by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, ſtripes, impriſonments;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11</note> tedious Journes, perils of waters, perils of rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, perils by his own countrymen, perils by ſtrangers, perils in the city, perils in the wilderneſſe, perils in the ſea, perils amongſt falſe brethren, wearineſſe, painfulneſſe, much watchings, hunger, thirſt, faſting, cold, nakedneſſed;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 8.</hi> Omnia praeſentia futura, terrena, caeleſtia, inferna &amp; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caeleſtia, omnia mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil parva, &amp; pro nihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo erant &amp;c. buc, <hi>Act. 15.</hi>
               </note> all could not ſtop, this champion of truth; Let death life, Angels, principalities, powers, height, depth, any thing op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: he for Chriſt, in the ſtrength of Chriſt durſt ſtand againſt all. So alſo the curch of Jeruſalem, giving anſwer to the people and church of <hi>Antioch</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what had been propoſed unto them, tels them in their letters that they had ſent it by men that had ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded their lives for the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Such as theſe are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious men, ſouls worthy the name of Chriſtians: becauſe valiant for Chriſt. I have read of one <hi>Romanus</hi> that was nobly born, yet ſo reſolute and ſtout was he for Chriſt, that ſufferings could not fright him, nor diſmay him, when
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:38127:58"/> his perſecutors whipt him with a whip made of cords that had leads faſtned at the ends; ſo that with whipping his fleſh was torne, yea and ſo much torne that his very bowells were ſeen, yet he cryed out to his tormentors; that he deſired not to be ſpar'd, neither did he wiſh his tormentors to give over,<note place="margin">Chriſtum diligit, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>it.</note> he was wiling to ſuffer to the utmoſt in the cauſe and for the truth of Chriſt. It is reported of one <hi>Sames</hi> a noble man, who had and maintained a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſervants of his own yet was depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of al his eſtate by the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and was compelled to ſerve one of the moſt abject and baſe of his own ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to whom the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> gave the ſaid noblemans wife, that by this meanes he might cauſe him to deny the faith. But he not at all moved kept his faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs in</hi> Moſes ſelf. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, where you have many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</note> ſtuck cloſe to Chriſt, willingly did he undergo all this wrong and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for Chriſt. Many ſuch precious ſoules have been in the world, many there are, and if perſecution ſhould ariſe even to death, it would be ſeen that there are Gallant-ſpirited men now that would ſuffer any torments rather then forſake the Lord Jeſus.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:38127:58"/> They would not harken to what fleſh and bloud ſhould ſay,<note place="margin">Verus Chriſti-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipulus propriae vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntati re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciat, et divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem ſequi deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derat &amp;c.</note> but to what the ſpirit ſhould ſay, and they would ſtrive againſt what is evill in themſelves, and ſearch what the wil of the Lord is and obey that. 'Tis the part of a good ſteward that is intruſted with much of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſubſtance, to laie out al for his maſter when his maſter requires it: the beſt of us all are but Stewards and what we have of life, parts, beautie, riches, honour, libertie, any thing, 'tis lent us of God; if God cal for it, we ought to give it all up for his ſervice and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. You that have truth of grace wil be ready ſo to do, ſaying, Lord all I have I received from thee, it came of thee: Io here I am ready to returne all to thee. My deare friends, conſider what you do now for Chriſt, what heart you have to what is good now, what delight in Chriſts ſervices now: you are likelieſt to hold out in ſuffering; that are diligent in the buſineſſe of the Lord, and in the work of your God now. Some men thinke they can ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for Chriſt, yet now they have no heart to the preſent ſervice of Chriſt, which God cals unto, they are negligent
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:38127:59"/> and looſe in preſent duties; Suerely ſuch ſoules who faile thus in preſent ſervice and duty, are not like to hold out in ſuffering times whatſoever they may ſay; He that in ſummer and fair weather is a ſlothfull, careleſſe, idle ſervant; is not likely to be a diligent laborious paines-taker in the cold, pinching, wet, ſtormy time of winter. They that are bred up in labour are beſt able to endure it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Tim. 4.7</hi> Non ocio indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ſed totis viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eonni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendum.</note> Chriſtians, excerciſe your ſelves unto Godlineſſe; do what God now ſets before you; do it faithfuly, do it with your might; you wil the better endure harder buſineſſe if your God cal you to it. They are men en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with a precious bleſſing, that uſe their al to the glory of God, that let not a hough be idle or unſerviceable.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> There are ſome that are clenſed and made free from all unrighteouſnes and uncleannes,<note place="margin">Pſ. 32.1.2</note> that have no wickednes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto them: theſe are bleſſed ſoules; theſe are precious ſouls; Chriſt paid a ful price for their deliverance from ſin, making peace through the bloud of the croſſe: they are by Chriſt brought home to Chriſt, their life is hid with Chriſt in God, they are raiſ'd
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:38127:59"/> up with Chriſt, and made to ſit together in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus, even already. Indeed in themſelves there is a body of luſt, corruption and ſin; and there is a law revealing ſin, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and condemning; ſo as it beleevers live onely by ſenſe, reaſon and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of themſelves, and as they live to men, they live both under the power and feeling of ſin and the Law; but if they live by faith in Chriſt, beleeving in the life, righteouſneſſe, obedience, ſatisfaction and glory of Chriſt, they live out of the power of all condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and unrighteouſneſſe. This is a precious life, and they are pretious ſouls that live this life of faith, that have all their aſſurance, confidence, comforts, flowing into them through a channel of faith, believing themſelves happy for what another, even Chriſt, hath done for them, and not what they have done or can do for themſelves. In brief they are precious, for take them as in Chriſt, as juſtified, they are as pure in the ſight of God as the righteouſneſs of Chriſt can make them, becauſe God ſees his onely in Chriſt, not in themſelves, he loves them not in the glory and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:38127:60"/> of Chriſt; theſe appear glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to God and in his ſight, becauſe they have put on Chriſt that is glorious. There are as many precious ſouls now, as there are ſouls cloath'd with the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt: they that were precious formerly, and could ſay, <hi>As he is, ſo are we in this world;</hi> they were ſuch by having Chriſt, by being perfect in his perfection, they were choſen in Chriſt, lov'd in Chriſt; they that are in Chriſt are precious now, and may ſay, <hi>As he is, ſo are we in this world.</hi> All believers are very like one another, and alſo like Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>6</label> There are ſome that are the Siſter, Spouſe, Wife of Chriſt, that have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed his heart, that he rejoyceth over, as the Bridegroom over his Bride; theſe doubtleſſe are precious. A precious Chriſt, wil have a precious Conſort: He is an excellent one, and wil have his Wife, his Love, his other-ſelf, to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious alſo: Chriſt glorious, his Spouſe glorious; Chriſt beautiful, his Love beautiful; they are alike; Bridegroom and Bride alike; their trimming is of one piece and faſhion, the righteouſneſſe of God.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:38127:60"/>
            <p>It may be a word of comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> to ſuch that live in places where they can find no good people, none that they can take comfort in, none that are lovers of truth, none that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the things of Chriſt. 'Tis ſad to Saints ſpirits to live in ſuch places, 'tis irkeſome to a man as a man to live in a place where he can have no ſociety, no company, fellowſhip with none: ſo with Saints to live where they can have none to confer with, none to diſcourſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, none to joyn with them in prayer and faſting, and holy communion: To ſuch let me ſpeak, it may be you can find none for ſociety, none that are gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious; yet be aſſured God hath ſome. When the Prophet cried out he was alone, and that he could ſee none but Idolaters, none but what went on in wickedneſſe; yet God ſaw ſome that were free, ſome that were haters and loathers of <hi>Baal,</hi> that had never bowed the knee to him. The Lord hath here &amp; there ſome, that are precious ſouls: Be not diſheartned chriſtians, be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mai'd, there are I acknowledge many briars and thornes, yet there are ſome Lillies; many weeds, yet ſome (though but a few) precious flowers; you may
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:38127:61"/> find none in great houſes, there may be ſome in cottages, none in ſilken gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, there may be ſome in rags, none on the high places of the earth, yet there may be ſome in the vallies; 'Tis indeed a thing to be bewail'd, that there ſhould be ſuch multitudes of men and women, in the world, and ſo few of them good, ſo few gracious. 'Tis ſad to ſee a throng in the way to hel, men preſſing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to deſtruction and to everlaſting perdition, and to ſee but now and then one going towards glory, towards e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting ſalvation. Wickedneſſe hath many that owne it, and wicked waies are ful of footſteps; but for goodneſſe 'tis not look'd upon, nor the waies of goodneſſe travel'd in: holineſſe is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like a poor man,<note place="margin">Cognatus pauperi nullus. Diviti cognatus eſt quili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet.</note> none cares for being of his kindred or acquaintance; but wickedneſſe like the great men of the world have many followers. This is a trouble to Saints to behold, yet as there may be by a Traveller ſome <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> found in a remote country, though but a very few in compariſon of the Natives: ſo ſome heavenly ſouls, ſome new-born chriſtians here in the world; though but a few in reſpect of what are
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:38127:61"/> are earthly and born onely after the fleſh. As a man may rejoyce much in finding one piece of gold, or ſome one pretious ſtone: ſo if you find but ſome one that is Godly, yet be comforted in hopes that there are more, though you for preſent know them not. And reſt aſſured that there are precioos Saints in this age in the world, as wel as in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages, and that you ſhal meet them all in glory.</p>
            <p>It may give you ſome hint who they <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> are, that are ſuch precious ſouls, ſuch rare Creatures, ſuch jewels; ſouls like Chriſt; holy as Chriſt is holy, pure as Chriſt is pure, that are excellent here upon earth, that are Kings and raigne in life by one, even Jeſus Chriſt,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are ſuch that enjoy a Chriſt within, that have Chriſt himſelf dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them, many dwel where Chriſt dwelleth, and ſo content themſelves, never conſidering whether Chriſt dwel in them, we have nothing nor are worth nothing if Chriſt be not in us; all that a man hath periſh and faile, and come to nothing if he hath not Chriſt. 'Tis Chriſt that is the ſouls all, he is the onely good, and the onely laſting good
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:38127:62"/> and ſuch ſoules may be ſaid to have ſome thing that have him, yea al things; but they that enjoy him not, have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, they have no oyle in their lamps: and being ſo, wil be ſhut out and not enter with the bridegroome into joy. But now all are ready to ſay they have Chriſt in them: have you ſo? examine your ſouls; are they delighted with Chriſt? is Chriſt that which delights you? doth Chriſt give peace? doth Chriſt drawe your hearts heaven-wards? lovers whoſe hearts are delighted with one they love, how are they drawn towards ſuch places where they may enjoy their love. Love is a loadſtone drawing ſouls to Chriſt. We cannot forbeare, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abſtaine from longing to be in more ful enjoyments of Chriſt if ſo be that Chriſt be in us. Chriſt is the great, the infinit good that is given out to men: they rejoyce infinitly that have this infinit good, their portion; they that have Chriſt have him that is good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond compare, and this is he that makes ſouls precious. There are as many precious ſouls in this congregation as there be ſoules enjoying Chriſt. And there are ſo many enjoyers of Chriſt, as
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:38127:62"/> there are lovers of Chriſt, that love him as their owne ſouls, as their owne lives nay much better then either. There are many that talke of loving Chriſt but their love to Chriſt is but ſuch as the hoſts to his gueſt, he is bid welcome more for his money ſake, then for any deſire of communion, and fellowſhip. If they may gain by Chriſt, they wil waite on him, if not they wil be ſtrange to him; you that talke of loving Chriſt, what doe you know of Chriſt?<note place="margin">Ex aſpectu naſcitur amor.</note> love riſeth from knowledge, what have you ſeene of him? have you ſeene his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſeen his glory, ſeen his comlines? He is altogeather lovely; have you ſeen this lovelines? have you taſted of his love? love is mighty in 'its operation love, the love of Chriſt coming in,<note place="margin">Socrates putat ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſam corpori, velut ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pergiſci a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moris ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulis, &amp;c.</note> ſtirs the ſoul wonderfully, it rouſeth it up, it ſets it a worke for Chriſt. Love produceth action, it ſets men up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on difficulties, and makes them go through hardſhips: doth Chriſts love do ſo with you, try, you may know if you deal faithfully in this thing; you know who dwels in your houſe, much more in your hearts, you know why you do this and that; what is it of all
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:38127:63"/> you do, that you do for Chriſt, and that from the life of Chriſt: <hi>Paul</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in his actings and precious in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and all was by Chriſt that liv'd in him; as many of you, as have receiv'd Chriſt, are happy; Conſider wel of it, whatſoever you are outwardly in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in forme, in poſſeſſions, in friends, &amp;c. I ſpeak not of, 'tis nothing; you are precious if you have Chriſt within, precious children, precious ſouls, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Saints, all of you precious, all of you jewels that have Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They that are precious are ſuch whoſe iniquities are hid and whoſe ſins are done away, ſuch in whom the Lord ſees no guile, ſuch that are holy, ſuch that are nouriſhed and carried in the boſome of the mercy and goodneſſe of God.</p>
            <p>Obj. But is not every ſoul a ſinner? do not all complain of their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, weakneſſes, failings errors, &amp;c?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A Chriſtian man is both righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and a ſinner, holy and profane, an enemy of God, and yet a child of God; for a chriſtian man by the force of his natural coruption may doe ſuch things as the word of God forbids, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:38127:63"/> as he himſelf as ſpiritual abhorres. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe did many things which were repugnant to the law of God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had cauſe to ſay, he was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready perfect.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.12.</note> Scriptures are not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſilent as concerning <hi>Abraham, Jacob, Rebeccah, Sara, Moſes, Job, David, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah.</hi> All good and godly ſouls take them as Saints, and walking after the Spirit, yet take them as in the body; and ſometimes they did not alone doe good things unperfectly, and leave ſome good things undone, but alſo do ſome evil actions,<note place="margin">See Rom. 7, &amp;c.</note> which were directly repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the rule of Gods law, and to their own renewed minde; thus may they be ſtil ſinners unholy in reſpect of their failings, weakneſſes, imperfect ſanctification, or ſanctification in part, but take them as juſtified, believers and in Chriſt they are righteous, holy, juſt: the ſin which they ſlip into is not laid to their charge, but is done away for Chriſts ſake in whom they believe, whoſe righteouſneſſe is their righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and their ſin, Chriſts ſin;<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus fuit peccator, ita nos juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſumus.</note> His by imputation, who is moſt juſt and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of himſelf, yet was the curſe and puniſhment impoſed upon Chriſt, to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:38127:64"/> whome ſin was imputed, that all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers may be reputed before God, by vertue of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, holy and perfect as righteouſneſſe it ſelfe. Thus you ſee how ſouls may be ſaid to be ſinners; take them as in themſelves and in the fleſh, ſo ſinners; take them as reconcil'd to God, as having Chriſts righteouſneſſe imputed to them, and beheld of God in that, ſo without ſin, without guile, no ſinners, but holy pure, undefiled, beloved of God, bleſſed Saints,</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are precious ſouls, precious in this filthy, ungodly, ſinful, wicked world, that from grace coming in act in wayes of grace and holines without, that let the inhabitants of the world be wicked, follow their Prince the Devil, yet they wil walke in holines, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Prince of peace, and King of righteouſneſſe. God in all ages hath ſome to witneſſe to his glorious truths, ſo in this age; ſome that are taught of the Spirit, led of the Spirit, that minde the things of the Spirit, that have the Spirit of God dwelling in them, and by the power of that Spirit in dwelling doe mortifie the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:38127:64"/> deeds of the body, and are raiſed up, and quickned by the Spirit of God within, to walke in righteouſneſs &amp; true holines, to ſerve God and own his cauſe, though the world with them that dwel therein oppoſe; they are excellent ſouls that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear for God in bad times, in the worſt of times, yea when 'tis not alone a hazarding their names to diſgrace and ſhame, but their bodies to be torne in pieces, to be burnt to aſhes. You that, are acquainted with ſcripture and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory may ſee every age, every yeare bring forth ſome ſuch gallant ſpirits, that were ready to lay down their lives to undergoe any cruel, vile, ſhameful death for the name of Chriſt, and the teſtimony of Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They are precious, for they that are faithful and choſen, that are ſuch as Chriſt is, continue good, let all the world be bad. A precious ſoule is an excellent <hi>Theophilus,</hi> and wil appeare ſo, let others be never ſo bad, let them be enemies to God, fighters againſt God. Times are bad now, and like for a while to be worſe, yet there are pretious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans: ſo ſome there wil be as long as the world continues that ſhal ſhine out
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:38127:65"/> as lights in the world,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.15</note> that wil be without rebuke in the midſt of a crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and perverſs nation, that wil run right on towards glory, let whoſe wil run croſſe, that wil keep their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments white, though others be ſoyl'd. I commend ſuch to you ſouls, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Chriſtians, for precious Saints, that abſtaine from all appearance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, that in heart and ſoul and life, clear to and follow after what is good.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Love thoſe precious ſouls that Chriſt eſteemes precious, nay that Chriſt hath made precious, that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God precious, that are the dearely belov'd of his ſoul, that are honourable ones, that are borne of the wil of God, that are attended on by Angels, that are for a ſhort time plac'd in the world and ſhal ere long be received into glory; let your delight be plac'd on thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ones, let your eyes be on them that Gods eyes are on, your heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe that Gods heart is towards: good children are apt to reſpect thoſe they ſee their parents love; if you be true children, rightly deſcended of the Royal line of heaven, you wil eye the outgoings of your fathers love, and as
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:38127:65"/> Bees ſettle where the Queen ſettles, ſo wil you where God; upon what family or ſoul the Lord hangs his love, you wil hang yours; where God delights to be, you wil delight to be all ſo. Conſider I pray who you love, what ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple it is you moſt affect, whether it be carnal, worldly, unregenerate men, or holy heavenly, regenerate Saints.</p>
            <p>Do you now deſire to know Gods jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> to be able to diſcern of theſe preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ones, to ſay ſuch are Gods children, ſuch are the friends of Chriſt, like Chriſt? you muſt have the life, ſpirit, wiſdome, knowledge of Chriſt, you muſt be taught of God, to know who are Gods, like God. <hi>Paul</hi> perſecuted the precious Saints of Chriſt, and was a deadly foe and enemy to them, til ſuch time as he was endued with wiſdome from on high, til God ſhone upon him, yea into him; and then knowing Saints he aſſociated himſelf with them, and was no longer hurtful but helpful. Many a ſoul is a ſore and grievous ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the people of God; I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded much of their enmity ariſeth from this, becauſe they know not Saints, they are ignorant what glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:38127:66"/> ones they are, in what a high eſteem they are with God, how God wil pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them that wrong them. Ignorance of Saints makes them ſlighted, reviled, defam'd, accounted as the filth of the world, and the off ſcouring of all things. Tis want of knowing the worth of a Jewel that makes it not prized; ſo of a Saint, that is a member of Chriſt, a child of God. The God of wiſdome give you wiſdome to know ſuch that are holy, that are Princes of the bloud-Royal of heaven, and to give them ſuch reſpect that is due, and reverence as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to them. This none can do but ſuch as have the ſpirit, this you wil do if the Lord give out the ſpirit of truth to guide you in all truth: if heavenly light ſhine into you, that light ſhining in, wil diſcover and manifeſt to you the children of light, and whoſoever you can find walking heaven-ward, you wil be glad of their company. Ignorance had a hand in killing Chriſt, and it hath ſome hand in all the wrong is done to Saints; the Lord free you all from it, leaſt ye ſhould through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance harme the darlings of God, and bring ſwift damnation on your ſelves.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:38127:66"/> God hath grievous threatnings in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture againſt Saint-wrongers, and there are recorded ſome heavy puniſhments that have been inflicted on them that harme the righteous; God keep you from the ſin, and ſo from the ſuffering. I might ad how beneficial 'tis for you to know who are Saints, and how much for your ſouls advantage to be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them, but I omit it.</p>
            <p>Happy are you that are of the number of theſe jewels of God, of theſe preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>5</label> ones. I do not know what your condition is in reſpect of outward things, and creature-enjoyments; but I can ſafely ſay you are a happy people, if precious, if ſuch as Chriſt, you ſhal all be laid up in glory ſhortly. God wil not loſe one of his jewels for a world: Heaven and earth ſhal periſh, but no Saint, never a precious ſoul, not a jewel that belongs to the crown Royal of glory. Theſe rare ſouls, theſe ſouls to whom Angels do ſervice, that are carried in the armes, in the boſome, in the heart of God, that are ſingular ſouls, choſen out from among thouſands by royal favour, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch in whom the eye of God can ſee nothing amiſſe, no defect,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:38127:67"/> no exceſſe, no preſence of ſinne, no ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of grace. Oh precious ſouls! Theſe ſhal be preſerv'd, Chriſt hath been at much coſt about ſuch ſouls, at more coſt then about any thing, at more coſt then about all the world beſides: he made the world and loſt never a drop of bloud, it cauſ'd him never a groane, but to make ſouls (ſuch as they ought to be) holy; it coſt him many a ſad ſuffering, he ſpent his heart bloud in the work; he took a great deal of paines to perfect them, happy you that are the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of Chriſt, his workmanſhip as a Redeemer; that have your ſouls fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned by him to be like himſelf, but are made new creatures, holy ſouls, bleſſed Saints.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Chriſtians, you that heare me, conſider part of your duty as Chriſtians, as men of God, as Saints; you ſhould labour for a Spirit of diſcerning, to be able to judge between men and men, to know the holy and profane aſunder, to know a Saint and a Devil, a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoule and a carnal wretch, a jewel from a common ſtone, a true Diamond from a counterfeit. God laid this as a neceſſary thing to be acted by <hi>Jeremiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 15.19.</note>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:38127:67"/> to know, yea to ſeparate the precious and the vile aſunder; the not doing, this was charg'd as a ſin upon the Prieſts in <hi>Ezekiel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 22.26.</note> Her Prieſts have vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated my law, and have profaned mine holy things; they have put no differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between the holy and profane, neither have they ſhewed difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the unclean and the clean; this may be laid at the doores of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel alſo, that put no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between, ſheep and goats, lambs and wolves, Saints and ſinners: are they pariſhioners, let them be drunkards, ſwearers, gameſters, whoremaſters, all are admitted to the Sacrament, never conſidering whether the word warrants it and whether within the liſt of Chriſt: 'tis enough their houſes ſtand, within ſuch a bundary of ground. Looke to it you that muſt give account to God, take heed what you doe, how you caſt Pearls before ſwine, give the childrens bread to dogs, admit them to your Maſters table that are not of his family; it concerns you much all of you that are Godly to know men rightly, that ſo you may not aſſociate your ſelves with the enemies of God, but with the Saints of God, not
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:38127:68"/> joyne your ſelves with the aſſembly of mockers, but with ſuch that praiſe God; not go in company with ſuch that are Traitors to the heavenly King, but with his obedient ſubjects; not frequent the ſociety of enemies of truth, but with the friends of truth; skil is required in all worke, eſpecially in Goſpel work. 'Tis needful for men to know the miſtery of their trade, to know what ware is good, what bad; ſo is it needful to be ſuch experienc'd Chriſtians as to know what is for the good of our ſouls, what for their hurt, to know their friends and foes aſunder. We ſtrive to know good money and bad aſunder, a true jewel from a counterfeit, gold from droſſe; why then ſhould we not ſtrive to know precious ſouls from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful wretches, lillies from thornes, hearbs from weeds; Chriſtians 'tis your duty to looke to what may tend to the welfare of your ſouls; let it appeare in this that you are careful by having no fellowſhip with the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, but as much as may be with the precious ſons of <hi>Zion,</hi> with ſuch that are precious Saints. I might ſpeake more of this Uſe, ſhewing how you ought to labour for a ſpirit able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:38127:68"/> between tares and wheat, between the children of Chriſt and the children of Satan, between them that feare God, and them that feare him not; and all this,
<list>
                  <item>In reſpect of God,</item>
                  <item>In reſpect of Good men,</item>
                  <item>In reſpect of Wicked men,</item>
                  <item>In reſpect of Your ſelves.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>God guide you into all knowledge by that ſpirit that ſearcheth all things, and is able to reveale all things.</p>
            <p>I have now but one Doctrine more to preſent to you, and I have finiſhed what I ſhal at this time ſpeak from the Text in hand, it is this,</p>
            <p>Let the places and times be never ſo bad, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> yet they that are Chriſts are like Chriſt; whereſoever truly gracious, Saints ſhal come, what times ſoever they may meet withal, whatſoever ſhal befal them, yet they looſe not their vertue, they are Saints ſtill. take a jewel, weare it upon your finger or in your boſome, 'tis a jewel, lay it up in a box it remaines a jewel, let it lie in the duſt 'tis a jewel, nay if it ſhould be caſt ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the dunghil it would be a
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:38127:69"/> jewel there, thogh covered with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is ver ſo much filth; So may I ſay of a wherein Chriſtian, a bleſſed Saint, one that the Image of Chriſt: A little tablet Chriſt is drawn, if it be ſet on high, 'tis a Saint there, if impriſon'd a Saint, if caſt out as the ofſcouring of al things, 'tis as vertuous then as at any time,<note place="margin">Non abii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> 'tis the ſame for vertue, for worth, for excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency when tis abaſ'd, as when it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, it looſeth nothing by evill times, by ſufferings or diſgraces, or any thing befalls it.<note place="margin">Non ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum malis. <hi>Acts 14.</hi>
               </note> Glod wil be gold in the fire, in droſſe, amongſt counters. <hi>Paul</hi> is <hi>Paul,</hi> when at <hi>Lyſtra</hi> they would have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured him as one of their Gods; he is the ſame when in priſon, the ſame in his bands and fetters as when free and at libertie, the ſame before the Magiſtrates as with mean men; in every place gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and ſtriving to magnifie the Lord. <hi>Daniel</hi> is as holy, as excellent in the court as in the Lions den, and in the Lions den, as in the court. <hi>Mordecay</hi> is not altered within, though his habit be changed without; he had the ſame grace within when he walked a foot and was cloth'd in ſackcloth as when he rode upon the Kings hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> cloth'd
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:38127:69"/> with Royall apparell, and the Crown Royall on his head, and had his enemy that wicked <hi>Haman</hi> his herauld. The three children were the ſame in the furnace as when they were over the affaires of <hi>Babylon: Moſes</hi> in the court, and <hi>Jethros</hi> ſheapheard; when he was reverenc'd as <hi>Pharaobs</hi> Grandchild, and when he was <hi>Jethros</hi> ſonne in law, was faithful, though inwardly chang'd, yet not outwardly; he was the ſame Saint in the field and in the court. The time would faile me to bring out what might be ſhewne unto you from the word of truth in the Scriptures, and alſo from many unqueſtionable Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, concerning ſouls that have mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted their ſincerity in all conditions, both in exaltation and in abaſement, in honour and diſhonour, in good report and bad report, when they have flour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed in the world, and when they have been at the place of execution, fire and faggot hath not diſmaied them, the fire hath conſumed the droſſe, the fleſh; not the pure part, the ſoul: Chriſt was Chriſt in them, both in life and death. There are ſome trees are greene all the year, in ſummer and winter, in heat and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:38127:70"/> cold in froſt and ſnow,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Non ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura &amp; tempeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, in &amp; cendia aquarum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſtiates, triſtes pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netarum configura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, &amp; luminari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um coeleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, quia ſuper na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turam e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vecti, Chriſto in recum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, in Chriſto vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vunt.</p>
                  <p>Non ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrahitur blanditiis ſeculi, quia audit in ſuavio rem vocem. Chriſti.</p>
               </note> ſo ſome ſouls al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies like Chriſt. Let the times be what they wil, let the face of the world alter yet they change not, let the world be turned upſide down yet they ſtand upon their legs, they are right let all the world be wrong, they like <hi>Noahs</hi> arke float upon the waters let all be under water; Let there be troubles below in the world, here on earth, they care not: Let there be terrible apparations above and ſtarry meſſingers portending ſad events, they are not afraid of ſuch evil tidings, they have a reſting place in Chriſt, Chriſt is to them for ſafty, for preſervation, every way a defence and a comforter; they change not, they alter not. Let the ſhip turne which way it wil the needle of the compaſse wil ſtand North, let the world turne about never ſo much they ſtand directly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Chriſt, and look heaven-ward: when other trees are without leaves and fruit they have both; when others; coole, they continue hot; when others ſparkes goe out, their light ſhines. When the hypocriſie of others to their ſhame is manifeſted, and they periſh: The ſincerity of the Saints appears, and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:38127:70"/> they flouriſh. Chriſts people have a marke by which they are known, let them be never ſo much diſguiſ'd, and miſ-nam'd by the world, Chriſt was God when the world abuſ'd him, though the world knew it not; Saints are like Chriſt, though under great ſufferings, <hi>As he is, ſo are they in this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt is unchangable, ſo are Saints, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Chriſt is the ſame to day and for ever, ſo are Saints, ſo far as Saints, enjoying Chriſt. Their light, life, holineſſe, &amp;c. in reſpect of Chriſt the root continues, other mens light ſhal go out, but the light of Saints ſhal never go out, it ſhal ſhine more and more unto the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect day. The light in them is everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 'tis Chriſt in them, they ſhal ever live, becauſe Chriſt their life ſhal live for ever in them. Nothing is able to deprive them of Chriſt, and therefore not of life; Chriſt is in chriſtians. Sin, law, wicked men, Devils, all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, powers of darkneſſe, ſpiritual wickedneſſes that are in high places can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pluck him out, nor deſtroy the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of Chriſt. Now Chriſt makes his dwelling like himſelf, every ſoul is holy like Chriſt, in whom Chriſt dwels.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:38127:71"/> Let it be whereſoever Chriſt pleaſeth, it wil be holy, holy in proſperity, holy in adverſity, holy in a Palace, holy in a Priſon, holy every where, take it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſpirit, and as it hath Chriſt within.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Becauſe they that are Chriſts have another ſelf in them, their old ſelf is done away, they have a new ſelf, a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſelf, that is God himſelf in Jeſus Chriſt: there is a diſcovery and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the rottenneſſe of old ſelf, and another ſelf is tendred, yea reveal'd, given in to ſouls, which is God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and he is the Saints righteouſneſſe, they are poſſeſs'd of God, and have God dwelling in them. Now I pray is not God the ſame in all places? and wil not God who is the life and righteouſneſſe of Saints make them appear the ſame, let them live in times and places that are never ſo ſubject to change? This is that which is worthy admiration, that God ſhould become the life and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of ſuch creatures as men are; and men by this means ſhould be ſuch excellent creatures, that their excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy cannot be done away.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Becauſe times of ſuffering, times of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:38127:71"/> tribulations,<note place="margin">Rev. 7.14</note> times of perſecutions are to them but as purging times, clenſing times, waſhing times. The body may be purg'd, yet continue a body ſtil, the man may have an il humour remov'd, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine a man. A houſe may be clens'd yet be a houſe, clothes may be waſh'd, the filth taken away, and the clothes be clothes; gold may be caſt into the fire, the droſſe conſum'd; yet the gold be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the worſe, ſo Saints may be Saints,<note place="margin">Aurum probat ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis: fidem, tentatio.</note> and like Chriſt, though they ſuffer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tribulations. Chriſt in troubles ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prares to them, and from that appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance that they have of him, they appear his. Saints glory is hidden, it this follows not that therefore they have no glory. We muſt not ſay, there is no Sunne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the clouds hide it from our ſight. They that have Chriſt have glory, and they doe and ſhal appeare glorious. Clouds, <hi>viz.</hi> afflictions, perſecutions, and tribulations ſhal fly away, and then ſhal their glory more clearly appear. Now there is much of Chriſt appears in Saints in a low condition in the world, as long ſuffering, patience, ſtrength to undergo trials and the like. Times may a little change ſomewhat of the outſide
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:38127:72"/> of a Saint, but it cannot take away the ſubſtance of a Saint.</p>
            <p>Let what hath been ſaid be ground for reproof to ſuch that are apt to blame times and places for making them bad, &amp;c. O ſay they we had not been ſo bad, we had not run into this evil, nor into that, had we not liv'd in ſuch a wicked place, had we not been acquainted with ſuch vile company, it was ſuch and ſuch that were the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our running into that bad courſe of life, of our taking ſuch headlong waies, and leaping into ſuch a gulfe of miſchief. We will not much queſtion ſuch complaints, whether juſt or unjuſt. I confeſſe 'tis dangerous living in bad places, and in being familiar with naughty people, much miſchief may they occaſion to ſouls, yet it makes not people blameleſſe to lay the fault upon the times or places they have to do in, this frees not from Gods diſpleaſure. <hi>Adam</hi> laid the blame on his Wife, ſhee on the Serpent, yet this freed neither from ſuffering. A Thief that hath ſtolen may plead his poverty, and ſay he was in need, yet may he be puniſhed and ſuffer what by law is to be inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:38127:72"/> one guilty of ſuch a crime: So an unclean perſon may ſay, had he not been guilty of folly had he not been entic'd and ſollicited. We might ſpeak in <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum</hi> in this caſe, and after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and yet wil not the offendor be found innocent. It were more juſt for faulty perſons to lay the blame on their own corruptions, and evil hearts; for times and places would not make them bad, were not they bad. <hi>Joſeph</hi> had a faire bait caſt before him, yet not taken. Much grace may preſerve men from evil in the worſt times and places. Caſt gold into mud, yet wil it keep its colour and worth; ſo a jewel in a coal-heap, yet wil it retain its vertue. A Saint wil be a Saint let him be amongſt Devils. Gods people ought to keep a daily watch over themſelves, eſpecially when in bad company, and as much as poſſibly they may refraine from their ſoſciety, becauſe many a good ſoul hath been ſpotted amongſt ſuch. I need not bid wiſe men beware of houſes infected with the plague, nor good men of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful places, they know as the one is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to the body, ſo the other to the ſoul. Remember, it acquits not ſinners to
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:38127:73"/> ſay that <hi>Adam</hi> ſinn'd, and had not he fallen they had not been thus tainted, nor ſo prone to evil; grace is offerd by, Chriſt, and they that wil be ſav'd, muſt by faith lay hold on his righteouſneſſe; if not, they wil be inexcuſable at the laſt day, and periſh Eternally.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis not enough for men to ſay that they are fleſh, and that the fleſh luſteth, &amp; draweth to evil, and over ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters them. Now wil that which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil prompteth into men (help them when they muſt give up their accompt to God) that 'tis with them as with <hi>Paul,</hi> it is no more we that do it, but ſin that dwelleth in us, or as it fel out of <hi>David</hi> or <hi>Lot,</hi> &amp;c? firſt to Anſwer that of <hi>Paul,</hi> conſider who he was, and of what ſinnes he ſpake. <hi>Paul</hi> was a holy and a Godly man, a choſen veſſel of God, can you ſay you are ſo? can you ſay Chriſt is reveald in you? that you encounter all temptations to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of your ſpiritual abilities? beſides 'tis ſhameful to bring ſuch a ſpeech from Scripture to patronize a courſe of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes, which is us'd by the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſome ſecret and privie infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Do not deceive your ſelves; God is
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:38127:73"/> not mocked. Take heed of uſing Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture as a ſtumbling-block, and let not that which was left for the good of Saints haſten your damnation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the ſins of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> I ſhal not ſpeake much now, you may by them ſee how apt the beſt are to fal, and ſo to take heed: do not any of you caſt your ſelves into the Sea, becauſe <hi>Jonah</hi> was not drown'd. By them may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort be ſpoken to Saints, if God ſhould let them be ſo farre fool'd by Satan as to fal into ſuch faults. Much more might be ſaid as concerning them, but I forbeare; the Lord in mercy hold up our goings that our footſteps ſlip not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis not ſafe turning our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the times, and to the places where we live, and the wickedneſſe of men with whom we converſe, this wil not make a paſſage to glory. The worſe the times and places are, the more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ought we to be; the more cheats are abroad, the more ſhould we look to our purſes. If the aire be generally infected, had we not need to be ſo much the more thisful of uſing preſervatives? But of care already.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:38127:74"/>3. There are ſome that accuſe their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings for what they do amiſs: they cannot reade and pray becauſe of their callings, and their callings make them breake the Sabbath. Pray lay not the blame up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what deſerves it not, your callings, if honeſt, were never ordain'd for your ſoules hurt, but for their good: ſuch that complaine of their callings, yet can find time from their callings to eat and drink and ſleep, viſit friends, and follow recreations and the like, that concernes their bodies.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Some accuſe their poverty, ſaying, we have not time to ſerve God; all we can do is to provide for our families, know this to be Godly helps towards thy family proviſion: So they cannot ſhew themſelves charitable they have not wherewithal. Can you not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the widdows two mites, &amp; how ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted? Beſides theſe, ſome lay the faultes upon their occaſions, upon the objects they meet withal, upon Satan, upon fortune, any where rather then on themſelves to be humbled; Let this reprove you; ſin no more, leaſt God conſume you; for were you good, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould draw you to wickednes;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:38127:74"/> you would ſay to all temptations, how ſhould I do this or that and ſin againſt my God?</p>
            <p>Would you know Chriſts people? they <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> are ſuch that in bad times are good, that owne truth when they muſt ſuffer for it, that are willing to die claſping truth in their Armes, or rather they claſp'd in truths Armes; that let multitudes meet them going to hel, they wil thorow the throng to heaven; let wind and tide be againſt them, they wil forwards; that are diſmaid with no frownes, nor daunted with no ſufferings. That are no milkſops of fearefulnes,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Oportet aut ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentem vincere, aut interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</p>
                  <p>Lacedae. monii hoc animo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, ut aut victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum aut victi oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</p>
               </note> but Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions of courage, that wil not deſert Chriſts cauſe, but manfully fight the good fight of faith, yea die in the battel rather then yield; for ſo it becomes true Chriſtians, to conquer or die, to go through in what they have a warrant from Chriſt to undertake, or elſe for Chriſts ſake and cauſe to lay down their lives. 'Tis reported of the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> that when they went to wage war, and joyn'd battel with any, they did it with this reſolution, that they would go home conquerours, or die conquer'd. All true, and gallant-ſpirited Chriſtians
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:38127:75"/> are of ſuch a ſpirit in whatſoever they undertake for Chriſt, being cal'd to it by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Pons a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go abrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſt.</note> they know there is no flying away without everlaſting ſhame. To deſert Chriſts cauſe, is an endangering of the ſoul to be deſerted of Chriſt. Beſides to fly from Chriſt is to go from him that hath al ſafety, from him that is ſtrength, from him that the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of,<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.</note> yet not as he deſerves; the words are theſe, My goodnes, and my fortreſs, my high tower, and my deliverer, my ſhield, and he in whom I truſt. Here are expreſſions holding out Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what the ſoul could, and as we are capable of hearing, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. 'Tis to ſhew that God is all in all to Saints, he gives in comfort, he guards and protects from dangers: this is enough to make any man valiant, to have divine power encouraging him, divine power comforting, divine power guarding, divine power at all times and upon occaſions to help; how can ſuch ſouls be conquer'd? 'Tis impoſſible; for he that is ſo divinely accommodated is ready to venture all he hath in the cauſe of Chriſt. A Chriſtian endued with divine power, is ready and able
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:38127:75"/> alſo to live and die with an Almighty Saviour; Chriſt to him is enough, Chriſt alone is all, he lookes ſtil on Chriſt, and obſerves him, what Chriſt ſayes, he ſayes; what Chriſt does, he does; let all the world take what courſe they pleaſe, do what they wil, neglect Chriſt, go contrary to Chriſt, perſecute Chriſt, yet ſtil the Saint that hath God for his ſtrength, God for his ſhield, God for his inſtructer, ſhrinks not, is not diſheartned: but holds on his way for truth, in deſpite of al that oppoſe truth, and though never ſo much ſlighted of truths foes, it cares not, 'tis ſatisfaction and encouragment enough to him that truth defendeth, favours him. Chriſt hath all his affection, and he hath from Chriſt all power to do what Chriſt cals him to, &amp; through Chriſt that ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens him he can do all things. By the power and ſtrengh of Chriſt, he is carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up on high, above ſenſe, above rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, above the world: he is raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove feares, above frownes, his ſoul like <hi>Jehoſaphats</hi> is lifted up in the wayes of God.<note place="margin">2 Chro. 17.6.</note> Chriſt puts in a holy magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, inſomuch that in Chriſts cauſe it feares neither fire nor ſword, croſs
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:38127:76"/> nor loſs, breaking of bones, tearing of members, men or Devils, ſo it may be one with Chriſt. In a word a ſoul that is truly Chriſts, borne of him, liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him is one, whom neither poverty nor death, nor bonds, nor any outward Evils can terrifie. Oh! ſouls you that this day heare me, what wil you do in bad daies? what in perſecuting daies? in the daies that fiery trials come? wil you then owne truth? wil love to Chriſt make you cleave to Chriſt? ſuffer for Chriſt? die for Chriſt? if it doth, then may it be ſaid, that you are Chriſts, and that you are no changelings; but true bred ſpirits, children of God in bad places and times like Chriſt. The Lord grant that though friends faile, riches faile, times alter, peace ſhould be remov'd, yet your faith may not faile; but that you may be baptiz'd with the baptiſme wherewith Chriſt was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd, though a bloudy baptiſme, and ſo being like Chriſt in life and death, you may be like him in glory.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Were I in a more publique place, I might ſpeak a word to the Parliament, the great counſel of the Kingdom; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting them &amp; praying them to have a
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:38127:76"/> care of ſuch that are godly, of ſuch that are like Chriſt, to deal wel with them, to preſerve them, &amp; make proviſion for them; for they ſhal be ſure of the help of them, whilſt they ſtick to Chriſt, the Saints wil ſtick to them. We have ſeen a miſerable defection by abundance of men, I will not ſay all, but doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe moſt have fallen off, becauſe they were not like Chriſt, and did not cleave to Chriſt. I ſhal forbear ſpeaking in this place what I might, were the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory ſutable; Good men are too much ſlighted many times, and bad men over much favoured,<note place="margin">Equidem Jehova contempum effudit in Principes.</note> God hath in a great meaſure caſt them out with ſhame, that were not friends to his precious Saints, but rather to the adverſaries. I truſt God wil give the Parliament a heart to caſt their eies upon, (and have reſpect of) ſuch that are the called, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and choſen of Chriſt. Whoſoever deſerts ths Parliament, the Saints will never, unleſſe they forſake Chriſt, which God forbid. If the Parliament ſhould be in ſtraits, Saints wil go in with them, if they ſhould be oppoſ'd, Saints wil help them, with body, ſoul, eſtate; their purſe, prayers, ſtrength ſhall help; If
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:38127:77"/> they ſhould meet with bad times the Saints would ſtand with them in the ſtorme. I fear, if the Parliament ſhould have the need of any hereafter, they wil finde few cloſing faithfully with them, but what are the faithfully of Chriſt. Methinks I hear a ſecret mutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amongſt many, that are ready to ſay, if troubles come, the Parliament wil have but few to take their parts, few that wil joyn with them; to ſuch whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perings I ſhal give a loud anſwer: if the Parliament follow Chriſt and take his part (as I truſt they wil) they ſhal be ſure of the Saints, all Chriſts friends, and have they theſe, I beleeve they need not care who is againſt them, or what oppoſition they meet withal, no though all the people of the earth be gathered together againſt them.<note place="margin">Zach 12.3</note> Let the Parliament ſet up Chriſt and favour thoſe are Chriſts, and then if all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the world were gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt them, they need not fear; for Chriſt would help them and take part with them; and if he be of their ſide they need not fear what man can do unto them: for Chriſt wil make their enemies fall before them. God
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:38127:77"/> wil make our Parliament-worthies ſuch to all their enemies,<note place="margin">Iſti incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibili ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore atque ſucceſſu gentes omes de bell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt, <hi>&amp;</hi> ſubjicient vel potius ſtirpitus cacindeut, <hi>Zach. 12.6.</hi>
               </note> as is ſpoken of the Governor of <hi>Judah,</hi> they ſhal be like a hearth of fire among the wood, and like a torch of fire in a ſheaf. And they ſhall devour al the people round about, on the right hand and on the left. All that oppoſe them ſhall be but as a little wood laid on fire, or ſtraw put upon fire coales, which would ſoon be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. God grant the Saints may be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured &amp; they that are truly godly be reſpected and car'd, for by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; &amp; then I doubt not of their flour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhing, and having friends to ſide with them, for they ſhal have all the faithful, and they are (through Gods bleſſing many. If this come to any of thoſe worthies ſights I pray God it may be a means to adviſe them, to have a care of Chriſts people, and then let them be ſure thoſe people of Chriſt wil have a care of them; And though they muſt venture all, nay die; they wil ſtand with them. God grant our Parliament-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies may conſid, er that though they have not the moſt with them, yet they have the beſt, though the Saints be leaſt for numebr, yet they are the ſtrongeſt for
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:38127:78"/> might, and ſuch that can though but a few, ſubdue many, five ſhall chaſe an hundred,<note place="margin">Lev. 26.8</note> and an hundred ſhall put ten thouſand to flight. Great hath been the experience that this Kingdome hath had of the Saints victories; of thoſe that went againſt their enemies,<note place="margin">1 Sam 17.45.</note> as <hi>David</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Goliah</hi> in the name of the Lord of hoaſts. Keep cloſe together Saints, keep with the Parliament,<note place="margin">Deus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet juſtis &amp; piis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliis.</note> and then I doubt not but all wil be wel, for God wil bleſſe the proceedings of good-men in a good cauſe; and what better cauſe can be taken in hand, then what is now in hand in England, the bringing Chriſt to his Throne?</p>
            <p>Let me conclude all with a word of conſolation to ſuch that fear bad times, and that have ſpirits troubled with the various toſſings in the world, and defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of men from truth, and other moleſtations that are all ready in the world, and that they fear wil come on to the further grief and ſuffering of Saints. Indeed there are troubles, the dayes are evil; times bad, and 'tis likely may be worſe; yet be ſure of this, they that are Chriſts people wil continue his people, they that are gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:38127:78"/> there will be ſome good ſtill, in ſad times, in the worſt times, ſome that in aſſured hope and confidence of Gods mercy in all neceſſities and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, cleave to the truth; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Gods power is Allmighty, his promiſes, moſt true; his mercies, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite; and that 'tis for their ſouls ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſſe to follow Chriſt, let what ſufferings ſoever come, yea though they looſe their lives. There are a rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that are enlightened, and from that enlightening they know what is beſt to be embraced, they know that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of troubles come now, yet to al that are in Chriſt, that are like Chriſt, that love his appearing, there will bereſt, there will be peace; there wil be bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; there wil be glory. Thoſe that are engrafted really into Chriſt, wil by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue receiv'd from Chriſt flouriſh. Bad times make not them bad, they will be good in any times, in any company, in any place. If exalted, good; if abaſed; good; if rich, good; if poor good; if in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, good; if in proſperity, good. Chriſt was a precious Chriſt in every condition, and they precious Saints in every condition. I know not what
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:38127:79" rendition="simple:additions"/> the times may be, but I know what they that are Chriſts will be, they wil be like Chriſt. As ſome trees continue green in every ſeaſon of the year, in winter and ſummer, in heat and cold: ſo ſome men good in all times, they are no changelings, they are ſtedfaſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, alwaies abounding in the work of the Lord.<note place="margin">Immobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſunt ſuper ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento Chriſto Dominum, in ipſum ſincera fide &amp; perfecta recumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> Let others totter, they ſtand; others ſhake, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable; others fal; they riſe, others be idle, they Labour; others be againſt God, they are for him. Conſider of this I pray, and let it cheer up your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. I know you are apt to ſay times are ſo bad you know not whom to truſt al ready, men are ſo deceitful &amp; wicked and if they ſhould be worſe you know not what to do, nor what wil become of you. Chriſt comfort you and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage you, and let what wil happen in the world, and let whoſe wil deſert you; if he never leave you nor forſake you, you wil do well enough, you wil be brought at the laſt to glory. You may receive comfort in hopes of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſome friendly ſouls, ſome Saints in the moſt naughty times; but ſuppoſe you be left alone, and there be
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:38127:79"/> none to be found, yet in this be glad, in this rejoyce, in this be comforted, that you ſhall find Chriſt, and he will be to you inſteed of friends, and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and companions, he wil be all to you. The Lord grant that none of you be diſheartned, nor fal backe, nor aſham'd of the Goſpel of the Lord, but that you may beare witneſſe to the teſtimony of Jeſus; and of this be confident your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour wil not be in vaine, nor any ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering unrewarded that is undergone for Chriſt and his truth. Chriſtian friends, whatſoever may make for your comfort I pray God give it you, let it be peace within, good company without, the benefit of ordinances, any mercy, that ſo you may be Chriſts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue like Chriſt, let places, times, men, the world with what is therein be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo bad.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
